how can you talk about renting you're
你怎么能说租房就是在
just throwing money away BS should I
浪费钱呢？简直胡说八道！我应该彻底
just dismantle these arguments once and
驳斥这些论点吗？
for all because there's some shocking
因为抵押
math behind a mortgage and most people
贷款背后有一些令人震惊的数学原理，而大多数人对此
don't know this let's get into it the
一无所知。让我们深入探讨一下。
meet safy the financial expert and
金融专家兼
entrepreneur is back to teach you how to
企业家萨菲回归，教你如何
take control of your money and confront
掌控自己的财务，并解决那些阻碍
the financial problems that hold us back
我们前进的财务问题。
most people fall into four money types
大多数人的理财方式可以分为四种，
that I've identified number one is
我总结如下：第一种是
avoiders and they'd hate talking about
回避型，他们讨厌谈论
money but if your partner simply will
金钱。但如果你的伴侣根本
not talk about money that's a huge red
不愿谈钱，这绝对是个危险
flag because % of the people I talk to
信号，因为我接触过的人中，有百分之百的人
do not know their household income 90%
不知道自己的家庭收入；90%的
who are in debt do not know how much
负债者不知道
debt they're in and 100% of the people I
自己到底欠了多少钱；而所有信用卡债务人，100%的人都
talk to in credit card debt also have
面临着同样的
trouble with that is shocking next up
问题，这真是令人震惊。第二种是
Optimizer they can get you to a very
优化型，他们能让你过上非常
good place they'll be investing we love
不错的生活，他们会进行投资。我们都喜欢用电子
to live in a spreadsheet but it can be
表格来规划财务，但过度投资也会适得其反。第三种是
taken too far and then the dreamer who
梦想家，他们
believes that success is one deal away
相信成功近在咫尺，
and they tend to fall into crypto coin
而他们往往会落入加密货币
scams like all this BS finally worriors
骗局。 所有这些废话最终都指向了爱操心的人，
they love to worry are we going to have
他们总是担心：我们会不会有
enough what if we run out of money
足够的钱？万一钱用完了怎么办？
typically they picked up worrying from
通常，他们的这种担忧是从
their parents who said stuff like money
父母那里学来的，父母总是说“钱
doesn't grow on trees and the problem is
不是天上掉下来的”。问题是，这种担忧可能会走火入魔，让
they become cheap and become so obsessed
他们变得吝啬，甚至
with $3 questions like agonizing over
对3美元的问题斤斤计较，比如
buying a coffee but everybody listen
买杯咖啡都要纠结一番。但是，大家
closely cuz I want to break down how you
仔细听，因为我想详细讲解如何
can change any of these types so Remy
改变这些习惯。雷米，
the only investment most couples make is
大多数夫妇唯一的投资就是
buying a house what is the alternative
买房，那么还有什么其他选择呢？
this is where real wealth is created
这才是真正创造财富的地方。
let's simplify the whole thing and I
让我们把事情简化一下，我
have four numbers that everyone should
有四个数字是每个人都应该
be talking about the first off is your
关注的。首先是你的订阅率。
this has always blown my mind a little
这一点一直让我有点惊讶：
regularly haven't yet subscribe to the
经常收听我们节目的听众中，有53%的人还没有订阅。
show so could I ask you for a favor
所以，在我们开始之前，我能请你们帮个忙吗？
before we start if you like the show and
如果你喜欢我们的节目，
you like what we do here and you want to
喜欢我们在这里所做的一切，并且想要
support us the free simple way that you
支持我们，最简单的方法
can do just that is by hitting the
就是点击
Subscribe button and my commitment to
订阅按钮。我向
you is if you do that then I'll do
你们承诺，如果你们这样做，
everything in my power me and my team to
我和我的团队将竭尽全力帮助你们。 我们的团队会
make sure that this show is better for
确保
you every single week we'll listen to
每周的节目都比上一期更好，我们会认真听取大家的
your feedback we'll find the guest that
反馈，找到
you want me to speak to and we'll
你们想让我采访的嘉宾，并
continue to do what we do thank you so
继续做好我们该做的事情。非常感谢！
[Music]
[音乐]
REM if someone's just clicked on this
REM乐队。如果有人刚刚点开这个
conversation please explain to me
对话，请告诉我
exactly why they should stay and listen
他们为什么要留下来听
to what we're about to discuss on the
我们接下来要讨论的内容，因为
basis that we're about to talk about the
我们将要讨论的是
things you've written in this
你这本书里写到的东西。
book if you are single and dating if you
无论你是单身约会、
are engaged or if you have been married
订婚还是结婚
for 25 years money is one of the central
25年，金钱都是
parts of our lives and most of us think
我们生活中最重要的组成部分之一。我们大多数人都把
about money as something to be avoided
金钱看作是应该避而远之的东西，
it's something we only talk about when
只有在事情出错的时候才会谈论它。这种
wrong what a terrible way to live and
生活方式太糟糕了！其实还有
there is a different way which is we can
另一种方式，我们可以
use money as a source of connection
把金钱作为连接、
possibility and joy and that is what
可能性和快乐的源泉。这就是
we're going to talk about today I had a
我们今天要讨论的内容。几天前，我
actually with um James ston who's the
和詹姆斯·斯顿（James Stone）聊过，
divorce expert he's a divorce lawyer by
他是一位离婚专家，他的职业是离婚律师，
trade but he knows more about divorce
但他比任何人都更了解离婚。
than anybody else and he said to me
他告诉我……
there's two things which cause people to
导致人们
end up in his office going through a
最终走进他办公室办理
divorce number one is cheating in
离婚的两件事是：一是出轨，二
infidelity and the second thing is money
是
problems in the relationship so I find
婚姻中的金钱问题。所以我认为
this conversation with you about
和你谈谈
couple's relationship with money um
夫妻间的金钱关系尤为重要，
because clearly one of the things that
因为很明显，
is most likely to end my relationship or
最有可能结束一段感情，或者
or I guess prevent me getting into one
说阻止我开始一段感情的事情之一，
is this financial avoidance that most of
就是我们大多数人都会有的这种逃避金钱的倾向。
us engage in you've interviewed hundreds
你
and hundreds of couples about money on
在播
your podcast what have you learned about
客节目中采访过成百上千对夫妻，你从中了解到了
our relationship with money in
我们与金钱的关系。
relationships from that I've learned
我发现，
that 50% of the people I talk to do not
我采访过的人中有50%不
know their household income 90% of the
知道自己的家庭收入；90%
people I talk to who are in debt do not
负债的人不
know how much debt they're in and 100%
知道自己负债多少；100%
of the people I talk to in credit card
信用卡
debt also have trouble saying no to
负债的人都难以拒绝
their children isn't that shocking of
孩子的要求。
those things 50% do not know how much
这些情况是不是很令人震惊？50%的人不知道
income they make because most of us are
自己的收入，因为我们大多数人只是
simply living by looking at our checking
看看银行
account and that's it the debt part kind
账户就完事了。负债这一点其实也说得通，谁会
of makes sense why would you want to
想
know how much debt you owe you don't
知道自己有多少收入呢？ 你欠的债，你
really want to think about it so you
真的不想去想，所以你会
ignore those emails and envelopes and
忽略那些邮件和信封。
the credit card debt part that is really
信用卡债务这部分真的很
interesting the idea that if you can't
有意思：如果你无法拒绝
say no to spending so you've racked up a
消费，就会累积一
bunch of credit card debt the same
大笔信用卡债务。同样的
princip principle applies to saying no
道理也适用于拒绝要
kids for me when I discover these I find
孩子。对我来说，当我发现这些的时候，我觉得
them absolutely fascinating but the good
它们非常引人入胜。但好
news is you can also change these things
消息是，你也可以改变这些。那么，
and women in terms of spending habits in
在恋爱关系中，男性和女性在消费习惯、
a relationship secrecy avoidance
避免秘密和争吵方面有什么区别呢？我们先从
roles men always describe themselves as
角色说起。男性总是把自己描述成
providers always that's what we are
养家糊口的人，我们从小就被这样
taught it's exists in culture the
教育，这种观念存在于文化中。
problem is of course what happens when
问题当然是，如果你
are not the top earner which is happen
不是收入最高的那一个该怎么办？这种情况
happening increasingly more now so when
现在越来越普遍。所以，当
I often ask them who are you financially
我经常问他们，
speaking if you're not a provider and
如果你不是养家糊口的人，那么从经济角度来说，你是什么身份时，
they're just stumped but there's got to
他们往往一时语塞。但肯定不止是
provider you can be a provider and you
养家糊口那么简单。你可以既是养家糊口的人，又是养育者；你可以既是养家糊口的人，又是
you can be a helper a leader there's so
帮助者，甚至是领导者。有
many different ways um often what you'll
很多不同的方式。 你经常会
see with women is discussions about a
看到女性讨论关于
secret bank account keep a little money
秘密银行账户的话题，她们会存点钱以备不时之需。
aside just in case we have to remember
我们必须记住，
that in the
在
US many grandmothers were not allowed to
美国，很多祖母辈的人都不允许
open up their own bank accounts that
自己开银行账户，这
happened in two generations ago and so
发生在两代人之前。因此，一直以来都有
there has been a rightful message that
一种合理的观念，那就是
has been passed down Orly keep a little
存
bit of money aside just in case whether
点钱以备不时之需，比如
it be physical abuse Financial abuse
身体虐待、经济虐待、
divorce Etc and I totally respect that
离婚等等。我完全尊重这种
message I don't think you should have a
观念。我不认为你应该拥有一个
secret account I do think you should
秘密账户，但我认为你应该
have an account that is yours only but
拥有一个只属于你自己的账户，而且
no secrets in a relationship what about
在恋爱关系中不应该有秘密。那么，
arguments as it relates to money and
关于金钱和
relationships what are the the cause of
恋爱关系的争吵又是怎么回事呢？争吵的原因是什么？是因为一方花钱
much is it hiding money is it something
太多？是因为有人藏钱？还是
else it's usually not hiding money
其他原因？通常来说，藏钱并不是主要原因，这种情况
that's very small extreme the biggest
非常少见。
phrase that I get from couples is he or
我从情侣那里听到最多的一句话是：“他/
she's a spender and I'm a saver so it's
她是个花钱大手大脚的人，而我是个节俭的人。” 这就
creating this identity that they're a
造成了一种身份认同的形成，要么是“他/她花钱大手大脚，
spender I'm a saver or they don't want
我是个节俭的人”，要么是“他们不想
to talk about money ever why can't I get
谈钱”。为什么我不能让
them to finally sit down with me and get
他们坐下来和我好好谈谈，达成共识呢？
tossed around everywhere when I ask them
当我问别人“达成共识”是
what is getting on the same
什么意思时，他们总是挂在嘴边，
page the answer is I don't know I just
回答往往是“我不知道，我只是
want to talk about it so when it comes
想聊聊”。所以，
to money yes there are the numbers that
说到金钱，当然，
we need to understand of course but what
我们需要了解一些数字，但
I often tell people the way you feel
我经常告诉人们，你对金钱的感受与
the amount in your bank account that is
你的银行账户余额几乎没有关联。这就是
why I speak to so many
为什么我接触过很多
multi-millionaires who still worry about
千万富翁，他们仍然为
money they think if I just have 50,000
钱发愁。他们觉得，如果我再多5万美元、50万美元、500
more 500,000 more $5 million do more
万美元，就能做得更好。你
well guess what I've had all those folks
猜怎么着？我邀请过这些人来
on my podcasts and they still worry
我的播客节目，他们仍然
about money that means there's two
为钱发愁。这意味着，要想
things you need to do to master your
掌控你
relationship with money one you got to
与金钱的关系，你需要做两件事：第一，你必须
know your numbers this is a language you
了解你的数字——这是一门语言，你
have to learn the basics of personal
必须学习个人理财的基础知识；
finance two you have to master your
第二，你必须掌握你的
money psychology that means you need to
金钱心理学，这意味着你需要
change the way that you talk about money
改变你谈论金钱
and behave with money so that you can
和处理金钱的方式，这样你
ultimately change the way you feel about
最终才能改变你对
money you do those two things you're
金钱的感受。做到这两点，你就能
relationship with money we'll go into
与金钱建立非常健康的关系。我们稍后会详细讨论。
all of those things and how you do them
所有这些事情以及你如何处理它们，
um on this point of gender roles
嗯，关于性别角色这一点，
obviously Society has changed in the
显然，在
last couple of decades in terms of
过去的几十年里，社会在
equality and more women are in work at
平等方面发生了变化，越来越多的女性
higher level positions in corporations
在公司担任高管职位，
in the SE Suite earning much more money
收入也更高。
this has caused
这导致了
typical gender roles and assumptions of
典型的性别角色和对伴侣关系中
what what each gender is supposed to be
每个性别应该做什么的假设发生了转变。
doing in couples and I'm wondering now
我想知道，现在越来越
with more women earning more money in
多的女性收入更高，在
many cases they're going to be earning
很多情况下，她们
more than their husband in heterosexual
在异性恋关系中的收入甚至超过了丈夫，
relationships have you seen new Dynamics
你是否观察到由此产生了新的动态
and new issues created because of this
和问题，比如，缺乏
in terms of like I don't know insecure
安全感的
men feeling emasculated or the woman not
男性感到被削弱，或者女性因为
being happy that she's contributing more
自己贡献更多而感到不快乐。
and I asked this because I had someone
我之所以问这个问题，是因为
on my podcast a couple of uh months back
几个月前我的播客节目里有人
who said to me that I think it's 70 or
告诉我，我认为有70%到
80% of women expect that their romantic
80%的女性希望她们的
partner will earn more than them but
伴侣收入比自己高，但随着女性
are earning more and more money I'm just
收入的不断增长，这种差距正在缩小。我只是
wondering if you've seen in those
想知道，在那些
couples scenarios where the woman ears
女性收入更高的伴侣关系中，你是否观察到过这种情况？
more and it's causing problems I've seen
这造成了一些问题，我经常看到这种情况。
time I think that we see different
我认为我们看到的是不同的
gender Dynamics um I recall one episode
性别动态。嗯，我记得有一期节目，
where I spoke to uh a young woman woman
我采访了一位年轻女性
and her boyfriend she was around 40
和她的男朋友。她大约40
years old she made way more than her
岁，收入远高于她的
boyfriend care to guess how much she
男朋友。你猜猜她
makes per
每月收入多少？
$20,000 $200,000 per month she has a
2万美元到20万美元不等。她经营着一家
business it's doing very well she's
生意，而且做得非常好。她现在
around the age of 40 now her boyfriend
大约40岁了。她的男朋友从小就
was never taught about money when he was
没有接受过理财教育，
growing up most people are not he never
大多数人都是如此。他从未
learned about investing certainly no one
学过投资，当然也没人
was telling him about a Roth IRA when he
告诉他罗斯个人退休账户（Roth IRA）是什么。他
was 12 years old
12岁就
and he had started his own business and
开始创业，而且生意
he was on the upswing he's making a few
蒸蒸日上，
thousand dollar a month good for him
每月收入几千美元，这对他来说很不错。而
she's making 200 Grand a month her
她每月收入20万美元，她的
parents started talking to her about
父母
investing when she was 5 years old so
在她5岁时就开始和她谈论投资。所以，
here we already see a difference not
我们已经看到了差异，不仅是
just in gender but in socioeconomic
性别差异，还有社会经济
status okay and over time that
地位差异。随着时间的推移，这种差异越来越大。后来
progressed so they come to me and she
他们来找我，她
says I want him to pay for dinner
说她希望他偶尔能付晚餐钱。
occasionally fine super reasonable he
好吧，他非常通情达理，
even said no problem I want to so he
甚至说没问题，我愿意。于是他
would take his credit card out and he
拿出信用卡，
would offer to pay and she would say no
提出要付钱，但她却说不，她
I want you to contribute more to your
希望他多往个人退休
IRA so in many ways she wanted him to
账户（IRA）里存点钱。从很多方面来说，她都希望他
pay she wanted to feel taken care of
付钱，希望被照顾，
which is totally reasonable but when he
这完全可以理解。但当他
offered she said no so this is the kind
提出要付钱时，她却拒绝了。这就是
of thing that I often see which is I
我经常看到的情况：我
think I want one thing but when I get
以为自己想要某样东西，但当我
that thing I don't actually want it it
真正得到它时，我却并不想要了，它并
doesn't make me feel the way I thought
没有给我带来我预想的感觉。比如，
it would I want to earn 50k more I think
我想多赚5万美元，我以为那样会让
that'll make me feel safe oh my God I am
我感到安全，天哪，我真的
earning 50k more it doesn't actually
多赚了5万美元，但这并没有
change the way I feel so I worked with
改变我的感觉。所以
this couple and I helped them understand
我帮助这对夫妇理解了他们
why they both felt this way about money
为什么对金钱会有这样的想法。
and you know from the outside it's like
你知道，从旁观者的角度来看，
this is so irrational if you make more
这似乎很不理性，赚得多就应该
just pay more if I were in that
多付钱，如果我处在那种
situation etc etc none of that stuff
情况下，等等等等。但当
matters when you are in the couple in
你身处其中，身处
that relationship you will feel a
那种关系时，这些都不重要了，你会有
certain way and we got to work with you
特定的感受。我们需要根据
individually not what everybody else
每个人的情况来制定方案，而不是听从其他人的意见。
says in the end the conclusion that they
最终，他们
came to was she wanted him to
得出的结论是…… 她希望他
occasionally pay for dinner but she also
偶尔付晚餐钱，但也
wanted him to fill up his Ira so this is
希望他能往他的个人退休账户（IRA）里存点钱。所以
what they did every so often before they
他们每隔一段时间就会这样做：在
went out to dinner she would give him
出去吃饭之前，她会把
her credit card and she would say here I
信用卡给他，说：“
want you to pay for tonight and he said
今晚你付账吧。” 他说：“
cool he understood it they went out and
好的，我明白了。” 他们出去吃饭，就是这样。
that's what they did now to us sitting
现在我们坐在
here we're like this dance makes no
这里，觉得这套做法
sense why don't they just do it this way
莫名其妙，他们为什么不直接这么做呢？其实，
of us has some irrational thing we do
我们每个人都有一些不理智的理财习惯，
with money every single one of us and I
每个人都一样。我
think that we are ready to actually have
认为我们应该好好
conversations about how we are
谈谈这些不理智的习惯。
irrational money is not just dollars and
金钱不仅仅是
cents on a page that's why you don't
纸上的数字，这就是为什么即使
feel good about money even when you have
你拥有的比你想象的还要多，你仍然会对金钱感到不安。
that's why you worry about money but you
这就是为什么你会为钱发愁，但你却
have never read a single book on
从未读过任何一本
Personal Finance we are all irrational
个人理财书籍。我们都是非理性的，
including me and when you get into a a
包括我。当你进入一段
relationship you got to acknowledge that
感情关系时，你必须承认这一点，
and then you got to say hey what is our
然后你们要一起思考：我们对
vision of a rich life together let's
美好生活的愿景是什么？让我们一起努力
build that if it means we do a little
实现它，即使这意味着我们需要付出一些努力。
dance about the credit card once every
每两个月刷一次信用卡，这样
two months fine do we both feel good is
挺好，我们俩都觉得舒服，
it fair then I'm good with it what's
公平吗？如果公平的话，我就没意见了。她到底是怎么回事？听起来
sounds like there's this battle between
好像
her mind and maybe her heart or it's
她的理智和情感在拉锯，或者说，
almost like the social expectation is
社会期望在作祟，
coming in but then her her brain is
但她的理智
saying no invest in the IRA and in Ira
却说不，应该投资个人退休账户（IRA）。IRA，可能
for anyone that doesn't know in other
有人不知道，
it's a retirement account a retirement
就是退休
account so she's saying invest in the
账户。所以她一方面说要投资
future but also buy my dinner well it's
未来，另一方面又说要请我吃饭。好吧，其实都一样，
the same it's the same we all have these
我们都被
things that Society has told us but then
社会灌输了这些观念，但
we don't quite agree and we're not sure
我们并不完全认同，也不知道该
what to do last time I was here we
怎么办。上次我来的时候，我们
talked about how you don't necessarily
聊到过，你不一定非要
need to buy a house in order to live a
买房才能过上
rich life and in my case I have rented
富裕的生活。就我而言，过去20年我一直租房，
for the last 20 years by choice and I
而且我通过
made more money renting and investing
租房和投资赚的钱
the difference than I would have by
比
buying a house and this is shocking to
买房赚的还多。这让很多
people like we saw the comments last
人感到震惊，就像我们上次看到的评论一样，
time people went berserk how can you
人们都炸了锅，说你怎么能
talk about renting you're just throwing
谈论租房，你这是在浪费
money away on rent and this is something
钱。 租房住，这种观念
we have been fed constantly for
我们从小就被灌输，几代人以来，我们都被灌输着“
Generations that in order to be
要想
successful you must buy a house so when
成功就必须买房”的观念。所以，当像
somebody like me comes around and says
我这样的人站出来说，
actually you should run the numbers
其实你应该算算账，
because sometimes renting can be
因为有时候租房可能
better people are shocked same thing
更划算时，人们都会感到震惊。同样，
with um if you want to be taken care of
如果你想要被照顾，
or you want someone to treat you or you
或者想有人款待你，或者
want someone to pay for the first first
想有人为你的第一次约会买单，情况也是如此。
date same thing when men come and they
当男人
talk about being a provider but in
说着要成为家庭的经济支柱，但在
certain relationships where they
某些他们
actually earn less I'll say to them if
收入较低的关系中，我会告诉他们，如果
we look at the numbers you're not the
我们看看账目，你并不是经济
provider so who are you and they're
支柱，那你到底是谁？他们会感到
stumped and that is when we need to
困惑。这时，我们就需要
start grappling with the idea that maybe
开始思考，也许
what we were told is not exactly true
我们过去被告知的那些观念，
for us in our situation today and that's
在今天的情况下并不完全适用。这
okay do you think it causes more
没关系。你认为，
not feeling like a provider when the
当
woman earns more money than the man from
女性收入高于男性时，男性会因为缺乏经济支柱的意识而感到不自在，这是否会在两性关系中造成更多问题？从
what you've seen not necessarily I think
你所看到的来看，这未必如此。我认为
that it is a different framework than
这与
we're used to yeah when we think about
我们习惯的框架不同。是的，想想
my parents for example my mom stayed
我的父母，比如…… 妈妈在家照顾
home with us my dad went to work single
我们，爸爸去工作，我们是家里唯一的经济支柱，一切都很
earner simple everybody knew where they
简单，每个人都清楚自己的位置和
stood what the roles were it was very
角色，这曾经非常
simple it's very difficult to do that
简单。但如今，要做到这一点却很难。
today housing is historically expensive
住房成本历来居高不下，
healthc care is expensive especially in
医疗保健费用也很高，尤其是在
the US and so you have two people
美国。所以，
earning in in urban cities you have
在城市里，两个人都要挣钱，而
young women earning more than men in
年轻女性的收入甚至超过了
20s a lot of us are trying to figure out
20多岁的男性。我们很多人都在努力弄清楚
what does this role mean for me and for
这个角色对我、对
my partner and for our relationship that
我的伴侣、对我们的关系意味着什么，这让事情变得很
makes it tricky I wonder if a lot of men
棘手。我很好奇，是不是很多男人
are just choosing to remain single until
选择保持单身，直到
they've kind of worked on themselves
他们完善了自己。
because I think actually that's probably
因为说实话，
the path I would have taken if I'm being
如果是我，我可能也会走这条路。其实，我的确是这么做的：在
until I was able to really provide oh
我能够真正“养家糊口”之前，我没有谈恋爱。哦，对了，我说的是“
the p word yeah and where did that word
养家糊口”这个词。这个词是怎么来的呢？养家糊口？
come from provide like watching my
就像我看着
father watching movies everything
父亲做家务、看电影等等。
exactly yeah no one ever says like you
没错，没有人会直接说你
are a provider but we learn it from a
是“养家糊口的人”，但我们从
million different uh perspectives and
无数个不同的角度学习到这个概念。
yeah I hear a lot of guys I mean when I
是的，我听很多男人说过类似的话。我
uh was living in New York and I had a
住在纽约的时候，有
lot of single friends topic of
很多单身朋友，我们经常
conversation was I'm not ready to get
聊起这个话题。 是不是总有人会说“我还没准备好
married I need to get to a certain point
结婚，我得先在事业上达到某个阶段”？
words for it and deep down there's a
关于这一点，人们有很多说法，但其实
feeling that we're often expressing you
我们内心深处常常流露出这样的感受：
know maybe I'm not ready maybe I'm not
也许我还没准备好，也许我不够好，也许
enough maybe I need to do XYZ before I
我需要先做某某事才能去做我
do the thing that I want and so part of
想做的事。所以，
what we talk about when it comes to
当我们谈论
relationships and money is like let's
恋爱和金钱时，我们会坦诚地讨论这个问题，
actually shine a light on that let's not
不要
be shy about it if you want someone to
羞于启齿。如果你想让别人为
pay for your dinner fine that's totally
你付晚餐钱，没问题，完全可以，
fine let's have that conversation if you
我们可以好好谈谈。如果你
want to be the sole earner in your
想成为家里的唯一经济支柱，那也行，
take and too often we don't have those
我们可以看看需要做些什么。然而，我们常常忽略这些
conversations we just dance around them
对话，只是绕圈子，一绕就是
for 50 years who should pay for the
五十年。比如，第一次约会谁该付钱？
first date then my answer is doesn't
我的答案是：
matter it would be nice if the person
这不重要。如果
who suggested the date pays but I think
约会提议的人付钱当然更好，但我认为
we spend way too much time focusing on
我们把太多时间花在了
the first date and way too little time
第一次约会上，而很少去
thinking about the next
思考接下来的
14,622 days it's like a couple who's
14622天。这就像一对情侣，他们
obsessed with the wedding fine you want
痴迷于…… 婚礼很好，你想要
a nice wedding great what about the
一场美好的婚礼，很好。那
marriage same thing with money first aid
婚姻呢？金钱也是一样，这方面需要好好考虑。
okay we can have that conversation but
好吧，我们可以谈谈这个，但
aren't you more interested in how your
你难道不更关心你的
partner thinks about money and talks
伴侣如何看待金钱、如何谈论
about money are they a cheap skate are
金钱吗？他们是吝啬鬼吗？他们慷慨大方吗？他们
they generous are they abundant did they
富裕吗？他们的
grow up the same or different than you
成长经历和你一样吗？这些都是
that is something we don't talk about
我们很少谈及的。
meanwhile we have five million YouTube
与此同时，YouTube上有五百万个
videos on who's going to pay on the
视频都在讨论
first date we are missing the real point
第一次约会谁来付账，我们却忽略了重点。
the point of money in a relationship is
金钱在一段关系中的意义
not just about the first date that's fun
不仅仅在于第一次约会——那只是为了
for clicks but it's about do we see
博取点击量——而在于我们对
money the same way do we connect are we
金钱的看法是否一致？我们是否能产生共鸣？我们是否能朝着
going to be rowing in the same direction
同一个方向努力？
or are you going to be doing that and
还是你会做这个而
I'm doing this and we can never get
我做那个，我们永远无法达成
aligned you can only make a first
共识？第一
impression once right and if you are a
印象只有一次，对吧？如果你是
guy this is just how I feel anyway if I
男人，这就是我的感受。如果我
go on a date a first date with a woman
和一个女人第一次约会，
and we have a wonderful date you know
我们度过了一个美好的夜晚，比如在
it's a nice restaurant and then it gets
一家不错的餐厅，然后到了
to the end of the day and then I turn to
晚上，当我转过头
her and say should we split the bill I
问她“我们AA制吗？”时，我甚至都说不出口。 说
face frankly I couldn't I definitely
实话，我绝对做不到，真的做不到，我绝对
couldn't ask her to play yeah I just I
做不到邀请她一起玩。是的，我就是做不到，真的做不到。
just could never and if I think if you
我想，如果你
anonymously pulled 10 of my female
匿名问我的十个女性
friends and said how would you feel if
朋友，问问她们如果第一次约会
on the first day the guy asked you to
男生就让你
pay I think privately they would say
付钱，她们会作何感想。我想她们私下里会说，
that's a bit of a turnoff that's a red
这有点让人反感，是个危险
flag that's an ick I think probably
信号，让人觉得很恶心。我想这大概
that's true and again goes to the power
是真的。这又回到了
of socialization right like culture is
社会化的力量，对吧？文化
very difficult to change we got to admit
很难改变，我们必须
that we got to acknowledge that and when
承认这一点。
I was dating I paid for dates so I don't
我以前约会的时候都是付钱的，所以我并不觉得付钱有什么
have a problem with it I like to be
问题。我喜欢
generous I think that when you are in a
慷慨。我觉得在一段
relationship you like to know that your
感情关系中，你肯定希望你的
partner is generous too now generous
伴侣也慷慨大方。慷慨有很
comes in lots of ways it could be paying
多种表现形式，可以是付钱
for dates it could be planning a trip it
约会，可以是计划旅行，可以是
could be being thoughtful and you know
体贴周到，比如，
buying extra toothpaste because we're
因为我们牙膏快用完了就多买几支。慷慨的
ways to be generous but generosity for
方式有很多种，但对我来说，慷慨是一种价值。
sure I paid for dates I'm happy to I
当然，我以前也付过钱，我很乐意这么做，我
like to do it but generosity to me is
喜欢这么做。但对我来说，慷慨的意义在于……
way more important to talk about that in
在
a relationship versus the date itself
一段感情关系中，谈论这些远比约会本身重要得多，
because chivalry you know this this idea
因为骑士精神，你知道，就是那种
that the man is to lead um in that
男人应该在这方面起到带头作用的观念，比如
regard and to you know open the door
开门、
yeah and open the car door and pull out
开车门、拉
the chair yeah but think about it I
椅子等等。但是仔细想想，我
agree with all that stuff I I'm I
同意所有这些，我
support it but think about what message
支持这些，但是想想当
that sends when you tell Men You're
你告诉男人“你
supposed to be chalous but there's no
应该有骑士精神”时，会传递出什么信息，却没有任何
real context no real around it and let's
实际的背景信息。
say you have a 26-year-old guy now who's
假设你有一个26岁的男人，他的
earning less than his girlfriend so he
收入比女朋友低，他
wants to be chivalrous but for him he's
想表现得有骑士精神，但他会想，
like well look at our bank accounts and
看看我们的银行账户吧。
so what I want to emphasize to people is
所以我想强调的是，
you can be chivalrous you could be
你可以有骑士精神，也可以
generous money is just a small part of
慷慨大方，金钱只是其中的一小部分，我们
that let's not over fixate on who's
不要过分纠结于谁在为
paying for top us okay and let's
我们买单，好吗？让我们
actually think about the important
真正思考一下关于
things when it comes to money we are so
金钱的重要事情。我们太
obsessed with $3 questions people are
执着于3美元的问题了，人们
obsessing over should I buy this coffee
执着于“我应该买这杯咖啡吗？
can I afford this appetizer on and on
我能负担得起这道开胃菜吗？”等等等等。
and on about $3 questions we totally
我们完全
neglect the $30,000 questions or the
忽略了价值 3 万美元或
$300,000 questions is this person
30 万美元的问题，比如这个人是否
financially aligned with me how do I
财务状况良好。 如果我和伴侣的财务状况一致，我该如何
even find out am I investing 5 to 10% of
判断？我每个月是否将税后收入的5%到10%用于投资？
take-home pay every month are we doing
我们是否
it together um do we talk about money
一起投资？我们是否
regularly and proactively and positively
定期、积极、主动地谈论金钱？
those things matter and they're actually
这些都很重要，它们实际上
worth hundreds of thousands of dollars
价值数十万
these $3 questions including who's
美元。那些无关紧要的小问题，比如谁
paying for appetizers or should I buy a
付开胃菜的钱，或者我应该买
latte irrelevant fact get get the big
杯拿铁，其实都无关紧要。但如果你找到了
answers in life right and you can buy
人生中最重要的答案，你就可以随心所欲地享用
all the appetizers you ever want what
开胃菜了。
relationship then number one is they
那么，一段关系中哪些财务方面的危险信号是危险的呢？首先，他们
don't want to talk about money if you
不想谈钱。如果你
don't want to talk about money red flag
不想谈钱，这就是一个危险信号，也是
the biggest red flag of all because we
最大的危险信号。因为我们对
could differ on how we see money we can
金钱的看法可能不同，
even have different values for a few
甚至在某些事情上的价值观也可能不同，
things but if your partner simply will
但如果你的伴侣根本
not talk about money you have a huge
不愿谈钱，那就说明你们之间存在巨大的
problem why if you can't talk about
问题。为什么？如果你们不能谈论
money then you can't even understand
金钱，你们就无法理解他们的想法，
where they're coming from and they are
他们也
not curious about what you want so how
不会关心你的需求。那么，
are you ever going to get on the same
你们又怎么能达成共识呢？
page think about this a lot of people
想想看，很多人
think we need to have the conversation
认为我们需要谈论
about money the con as if it's one
金钱，但事实并非如此。 这只是一次
conversation about raising kids no
关于养育孩子的对话，不，
you'll will have thousands in your life
你一生中会和成千上万的人谈论金钱，这才是正常的。
that's the way it should be money is
金钱和
very much like parenting not like uh
育儿非常相似，不像“
should we play pickle ball or tennis
我们今天该打匹克球还是网球”这种
today irrelevant so we want to have lots
无关紧要的问题。所以我们需要进行很多
of conversations about money and that
关于金钱的对话，这
means we need to first of all be willing
意味着我们首先需要愿意
to talk about it and then we need to
谈论它，然后我们需要
find a way to have fun doing it why
找到一种有趣的方式来谈论它。为什么
don't we and who doesn't is it men is it
我们不谈论金钱？谁不谈论金钱？是男人
women that don't do it more more or
不谈论金钱，还是女人不
who's not talking about money and why
谈论金钱？或者谁不谈论金钱？为什么
aren't they talking about it it's not
他们不谈论金钱？这
with gender terms of who does or doesn't
与性别无关，与谁谈论或不
talk about money there are avoiders
谈论金钱无关。有些人是回避型人格，
that's one of four categories uh money
这是我总结的四种金钱类型之一。回避型人格
types that I've identified avoiders hate
讨厌
talking about money and they will use a
谈论金钱，他们会使用
series of conscious and unconscious
一系列有意识和无意识的
techniques to avoid talking about money
技巧来避免谈论金钱。
they'll say things like um uh why why do
他们会说“嗯……为什么？为什么
you always have to talk about money
你总是要谈论金钱？
can't we just have a nice night out or
我们不能出去玩一晚上吗？”或者“
you're so much better at this you just
你在这方面比我强多了。” 你只要
handle it you're just so much savier at
处理好就行了，你在这方面比别人懂得多得多。这就是个
this stuff that's an avoider do they
逃避型人格。他们
know their own financial situation no so
了解自己的财务状况吗？不了解。所以
they don't know their own financial
他们不了解自己的财务
situation and they don't want to talk
状况，也不想谈论
about it correct we and by the way we
它，对吧？顺便说一句，我们
all have something like this it could be
每个人都有类似的事情，可能是
our fitness it could be our relationship
健身，可能是
with our parents there's something in
和父母的关系。
our life that we know we should deep
生活中总有一些事情，我们内心深处知道应该
down but we avoid it yeah and there's no
去做，但我们却逃避。是的，而且
there's no immediate consequence like if
没有直接的后果。比如，如果
I don't call my college friend it's fine
我不给大学朋友打电话，没关系，
I could probably call him tomorrow and
我明天可能再打，
you can go on and on and on like that
你可以一直这样拖下去，
until one day you can same thing with
直到有一天，
procrastinate on Fitness or money
健身和金钱一样，很容易拖延，
because it's not like your house is
因为这又不像房子会
being taken away or even your cables
被没收，或者有线电视会被
being shut off it'll probably be fine
停掉，可能暂时没什么大不了的，
until one day you hit this brick wall
直到有一天你撞上了一堵墙，事情就真的发生了。这就是
not so that's the avoider that's the
逃避型人格，这是
first money type yep next up Optimizer I
第一种金钱类型。是的，接下来是优化型人格。我
have a soft spot because I am an
对优化型人格情有独钟，因为我就是个优化型人格。
Optimizer optimizers we love to live in
优化型人格喜欢生活在电子
the spreadsheet it's like let me sit and
表格里，就像…… 我坐在那里
calculate this and what if I run a
计算这个，如果我运行
compound interest calculation a Monte
复利计算，
Carlo calculation and what if we do this
蒙特卡罗计算，如果我们这样做呢？
but not that I love calculating
但不是这样的，我喜欢计算
everything and left alone I would sit
一切，如果没人管，我会一辈子都坐在
there and do that for the rest of my
那里做这个。
life okay the problem is you can take it
好吧，问题是，你可能会做得过头。
a little too far now I don't think I've
我觉得我还没
taken it too far perf I think I'm
做得太过头，完美！我觉得
perfect on my spreadsheets but my wife
我的电子表格做得完美无缺，但我妻子
has taught me enough's enough we we've
教会了我适可而止。我们已经
won that part of life let's focus on
赢得了人生的这一部分，让我们关注
another part connection and fun and
另一部分：人际关系、乐趣和
experience are these people often
体验。这些人经常被
thought of as boring yes they are they
认为很无聊吗？是的，他们确实很无聊，从本质上讲，
are deep down they are boring I was
他们很无聊。
boring when I was sitting there thinking
当我坐在那里想着
money is only about numbers it's not
金钱只是数字的时候，我也很无聊。
money is about Adventure and possibility
金钱不是关于冒险、可能性
and generosity and you will often find
和慷慨的。你经常会遇到一些
optimizers I'll give them a challenge
精于算计的人。我会给他们一个挑战，比如
I'll give him a $100 challenge Al you
给他们一个100美元的挑战：“艾尔，你
have to take $100 in the next week and
必须在下周拿出100美元
spend it on yourself they cannot do it
花在自己身上。”他们做不到，
they will spend it on their dog they'll
他们会花在狗身上，
spend it on their kid they'll spend it
花在孩子身上，花在
on their partner but they will not do it
伴侣身上，但他们不会为
for themselves and I go go why didn't
自己花。然后我就问：“为什么？”
you do it they go R do you know that if
你没做到吗？他们说R。你知道吗，如果
you put $100 in the S&amp;P 500 and you
你把100美元投到标普500指数，然后让它在
compound that for the next 45 years
接下来的45年里复利增长，
it'll turn into this much I go I don't
它会变成这么多？我说，我才不在乎呢，赶紧把
give a spend the money because
钱花掉，因为
money is not simply meant to be hoarded
钱不是用来囤积的，对吧？
right it's meant to create a rich life
它是用来创造富足生活的。
and when you have
当你有理财
optimizers the thing is they can get you
优化师的时候，他们能把你带到
to a very good place they will probably
一个非常好的位置，他们可能
have your account set up dialed in
会把你的账户设置得非常完美，
they'll be investing great they're going
他们会进行很棒的投资，他们会
to be very proud look at the compound
非常自豪，看看
interest returns all that is fantastic
复利的回报，这一切都很棒，
but it can be taken too far these are
但是过度投资也会适得其反。
out that they had like $9 million some
有些人去世后，你才发现他们有900万美元的
saving account what a waste they never
存款，真是浪费，他们从未
tasted the caviar but they've got yeah
品尝过鱼子酱，但他们确实拥有。是的，
like people send these newspaper
就像人们到处传播这样的报纸
articles around like oh local librarian
文章，比如“哦，当地图书馆员
discovered to have $9 million and I go
被发现有900万美元”，我说，真是个
what a tragedy what a tragedy to live a
悲剧，真是个悲剧，过着比
smaller life than you have to I want you
你应有的更简朴的生活。我希望你
to save I want you to invest but I also
储蓄，我希望你投资，但我也
want you to try a nice meal or if you
希望你尝试一顿美食，或者如果你
don't like nice food or you don't want a
不喜欢美食，或者不想买
nice t-shirt also fine get super
漂亮的T恤？没关系，那就
generous give that money surprise the
慷慨解囊，给小费，给
people around you tip 50% so those are
周围的人一个惊喜，比如50%的小费。这些人属于“
optimizers the third category is
精打细算型”。第三类是“忧虑型”，
worriors they love to worry typically
他们喜欢忧虑，通常是
they picked up worrying from their
从父母那里学来的，
parents almost always and their entire
几乎无一例外。他们
relationship with money is worry are we
与金钱的关系就是忧虑：我们会不会
going to have enough what if we run out
有足够的
of money what if we don't have enough to
钱？万一钱用完了怎么办？万一
pay at the gas station
加油站没钱怎么办？
and often times it's very surprising
很多时候，这很令人惊讶，
because I told you that 50% of couples
因为我之前说过，50%的夫妻
don't know how much they make right so
不知道自己赚多少钱，对吧？所以
they'll say like we need more we don't
他们会说，我们需要更多钱，我们
have enough right now and I'll ask them
现在钱不够。我会问他们，
how much do you think you make this just
你觉得你
around $70,000 a year okay we add up all
一年能赚多少钱？就在几周前的一个播客节目里，他们以为自己年收入7万美元左右。好吧，我们把
their stuff they make $120,000 a year so
他们的收入加起来，他们一年能赚12万美元。所以
I go well here you go you you wanted to
我说，你本来想
make an extra 40K you actually make 50K
多赚4万美元，结果你实际赚了5万美元，
more than you thought do you feel any
感觉
better and she
好些了吗？她说，
goes no because the way you feel about
没有，因为你的感觉 对
money is highly uncorrelated to the
金钱的看法
amount in your bank account so worriers
与你的银行账户余额高度无关，所以焦虑的人才会如此焦虑，
worry that's how they relate they can't
他们无法
imagine any other relationship to money
想象与金钱的其他关系。
and my job is to help them realize first
我的工作就是帮助他们认识到这一点。
of all let's actually look at your
首先，让我们来看看你的财务状况。
numbers let me help you understand what
让我帮你理解这些数字的
it means do you have enough what does it
含义：你拥有的足够吗？拥有足够的钱
take to have enough and then can you
需要什么？然后，你能否
start to develop a new relationship with
开始与金钱建立一种新的关系？
money it's almost like a new taste bud
这就像培养新的味蕾一样。
I'm never going to tell you to eat
我永远不会强迫你吃你
tomatoes if you hate Tomatoes but I am
讨厌的西红柿，但我会
going to teach you maybe you like okra
教你。也许你喜欢秋葵，
and we can develop a new taste for
我们可以培养对
that finally the
秋葵的喜爱。最后，
dreamer the dreamer believes that
梦想家们相信
success is one deal away if we just
成功近在咫尺，只要我们
close this deal if I just get this thing
完成这笔交易，只要我得到这个东西。
and they tend to fall into get-rich
他们往往会落入
quick schemes lots of scams ml m a lot
快速致富的陷阱，各种骗局层出不穷，包括传销、
of crypto shitcoin scams like all this
加密货币骗局等等。
BS but they are extremely resistant to
但他们对
calm lowcost long-term investing in
冷静、低成本的长期投资却极其抵触，换句话说，
build real wealth they think it's boring
他们觉得大多数人积累真正财富的方式很枯燥。
they even have little phrases like uh I
他们甚至会说“我
don't want to be stuck in a ninetto five
不想被困在……”之类的话。
like those suckers I'm like that sucker
像那些九到五的人，我心想，他们挣的钱是你
makes 10 times what you make what are
十倍，
you talking about but they have simply
你在说什么？但他们只是被“再做
been surrounded with the idea one more
一笔交易，我就能成功了”的想法包围着。和他们
be hard to be married to it's impossible
结婚肯定很难，简直不可能，真的非常非常
it's really really difficult they don't
难。他们
not only do they not want to talk about
不仅不想谈
money when they finally do talk about
钱，就算最后谈了，也
money they're almost living in a
几乎活在
different world often you will find that
另一个世界里。你会发现，
dreamers can only dream because they are
梦想家之所以能做梦，是因为他们
life usually their partner and if their
生活中有人在资助他们，通常是他们的伴侣。如果他们的
partner were to leave for example the
伴侣离开，比如，他们的“
House of Cards would collapse and
纸牌屋”就会崩塌。事实上，
actually that's usually the only thing
这通常是唯一
that gets them to truly change so if
能让他们真正改变的事情。所以，如果
we've got these four money types um the
我们有这四种金钱类型：逃避型、
avoider the optimizer the worrior the
优化型、奋斗型和
dreamer in your view who lives a happier
梦想家，你认为谁的生活更幸福？
life you can live a happy life with any
你可以和任何一种类型的人过上幸福的生活，
of these also you can change any of
你也可以改变任何一种
these types but on average one person's
类型，但平均来说，可能只有一个人会……
going to probably I mean I I'm the
我是
optimizer and I'm pretty happy so is
优化型，我很幸福。所以这就是
that is that the answer yeah optimizers
答案吗？是的，优化型
are great they love their spreadsheet um
很棒，他们喜欢他们的电子表格。 嗯，
I think that uh the warrior clearly is
我觉得战士显然
not going to live the happiest life the
不会过上最幸福的生活，而
dreamer is actually quite happy yeah the
梦想家实际上相当幸福。是的，
dreamer is quite happy they live in
梦想家相当幸福，他们生活在
optimism yeah they're living in a world
乐观之中。是的，他们生活在一个不真实的世界里，这个世界
that's not real it's subsidized by
是由
somebody else they're always optimistic
别人补贴的。他们总是对
about what's going to happen next week
下周、
next month next year never realizing the
下个月、明年会发生什么充满乐观，却从未意识到
catastrophe that they are leaving behind
他们身后留下的灾难。这就是问题的关键所在。
them that's that's the whole issue this
这也是
the reason I wrote the book is it's one
我写这本书的原因：
your own when you're single you can be
单身的时候，你可以
irresponsible you can be an Optimizer
不负责任地花钱，你可以成为一个精打细算的人。
but when you're in a relationship it's
但是，当你身处一段感情关系中时，一切都
not about you anymore it's about the two
不再以你为中心，而是以
of you as a unit and so you have to
你们两个人为一个整体。所以，你必须
deeply understand yourself and then you
深刻地了解自己，然后你
have to be willing to communicate with
必须愿意与
your partner and really create a rich
你的伴侣沟通，真正为你们两个人创造一个丰富的
life vision for the two of you most
生活愿景。
couples I talk to have no vision for
我接触过的大多数情侣都没有理财愿景，这就是
their money that's why they fight over
为什么他们会为了谁在
who spent $50 at Target I go who gives a
塔吉特百货花了50美元而争吵。我想说，谁会在乎塔吉特百货？
about Target financial problems are
财务问题
almost never about overspending at
几乎从来都不是源于在
Target the biggest problem with couples
塔吉特百货过度消费。 情侣和金钱之间最大的问题
and money is they have no Rich Life
是他们没有“富足生活”的
vision what is money to us what do we
愿景。金钱对我们来说意味着什么？我们
want to use money for how do we want to
想用金钱做什么？我们希望
feel about it so they're confronted with
对金钱有怎样的感受？所以他们每周都要面对
a thousand different decisions with
无数个与
their money every week and they have no
金钱相关的决定，却没有任何
vision to guide them this is for us this
愿景来指引他们。哪些钱适合我们？哪些钱
is not for us one of the things I've
不适合我们？我一直很
always wondered in relationships
疑惑，在恋爱关系中，有
is how many couples know how much money
多少情侣知道
the other couple has in their savings
对方的储蓄
account and their total sort of
账户里有多少钱？他们的
Investment Portfolio because I've never
投资组合总额是多少？因为我从来没有
been in a relationship where I mean I've
过这样的恋爱经历——我
only really been in two relationships
其实只谈过两次恋爱，
you could say but I've been with you
但这些年来我约会过很多
know dated people over the years and
人，也和
been with my current partner for many
现在的伴侣在一起很多很多
many many years but even my current
年了——但即使是我现在的
partner has no idea how much money I
伴侣也不知道我有多少钱。我完全不知道。我们什么时候才能谈这个？
conversation probably never should we
可能永远都不会谈。我们应该现在就说出来吗？还是现在就说出来？
out I've just never had the conversation
我从来没谈过这个问题。
if we if you need something we can get
如果我们需要什么，我们可以帮你。是的，
that in my life okay so I I made a
我的人生一直都是这样。好吧，我
mistake in my own relationship I was uh
在自己的恋爱关系中犯了个错误。我和
dating my now wife for many years and at
我现在的妻子交往了很多年…… 有
one point she had asked some question
一次，她问了我一些
about her 401k or something and I said
关于她401k退休账户之类的问题，我说
well there is a book called I will teach
有一本书叫《教
you to be rich here's a copy of it and I
你如何致富》，这是给你的。我当时只是
was joking around with her and so it I
跟她开玩笑，结果就
ended up learning all about her finances
了解了她所有的财务状况，对
so I knew about her entire Financial
她的财务状况了如指掌。我当时完全
picture it didn't occur to me to talk
没想到要跟她谈
about my own and a little while later
自己的财务。过了一会儿，
she she very assertively said this
她很肯定地说：“这
doesn't feel fair you know everything
不公平，你知道
about my finances but I don't know about
我所有的财务状况，但我却不知道
yours
你的。”
and I realized I violated my own rule in
我这才意识到，我违反了
chapter n of my first book which is talk
我第一本书第n章里写的规则——
about money early on talk about it
尽早谈论金钱，并定期谈论它。
regularly so we talked about it we
所以我们谈了起来，那次谈话
about is actually one of the most
实际上是
memorable conversations we had because
我们之间最难忘的对话之一，因为我们
talked about the numbers talked about my
谈到了数字，谈到了
pride in how hard I had worked to build
我为自己
my business and invest for 20 years 25
20年、25年来努力建立事业和投资而感到自豪，
years and um and then we talked about
然后我们谈到了这对
what it meant for us like what kind of
我们意味着什么，比如
Life do we want to have do we want to
我们想要什么样的生活，我们想
live here do we want to live there do we
住在这里还是那里，我们
want to have kids do we want to eat this
想要孩子吗，我们想吃什么
type of food travel like that
样的食物，想去哪里旅行
conversation about possibility is the
等等。
conversation I want every couple to have
我希望每对情侣都能谈谈可能性，
because it's about
因为这关乎
possibility and you can start to dream
可能性，你可以开始做梦，
and that dream is important you can get
而梦想很重要。
to the logistics of course we'll get to
当然，我们可以探讨具体的操作细节，
that but so few of us still
但我们当中很少有人还能用
dream with our money but you know that I
金钱来做梦。我知道，像
think for someone like you who is the
你这样
optimizer and who's probably quite proud
擅长优化的人，可能对
of the system you've created love
你创建的“爱的系统”相当自豪，
systems but there's going to be so many
但现在有很多正在
relationship and they are maybe early in
恋爱中的人，他们可能还处于恋爱初期，也许和
been with a person six months they've
对方
taken them out on lots of nice dates and
交往了六个月，约会过很多次，
they have $1,000 in their savings
储蓄账户里有1000美元，
account and their partner has no idea
而他们的伴侣毫不知情。
and they're thinking
他们心想，
if I tell my partner what's in this bank
如果我告诉伴侣
account she is going to be shocked or he
账户里有多少钱，她/他会大吃一惊，然后
is going to be shocked and they are
他们会
going to leave me so I'm keeping this
离开我，所以我才保守这个
a secret because they are living
秘密，因为他们误以为
illusion that I have more than I
我比
actually have yeah but remember this
实际拥有的更多。但是记住，
just because you don't have as much
仅仅因为你没有
money as you want doesn't mean that you
你想要的那么多钱，并不意味着你
are less of a person what could be more
低人一等。
completely agree I completely agree what
完全同意，我完全同意。还有什么比直接
could be more appealing than saying you
说“你
know what
知道吗，
would you be open to talk about our
你愿意谈谈我们的
finances we're getting a little bit
财务状况吗？”更有吸引力的呢？我们现在关系有点
serious you know I know we're kind of
认真了，你知道，我们正在
talking about taking the next step I
考虑下一步，我
think money is going to be an important
认为金钱会是其中很重要的
part of it I know it is for me and I
一部分，我知道对我来说是这样。我
wonder if we could sit down and talk
想知道我们是否可以先坐下来谈谈，
about it first just being proactive how
主动一点。有
many people watching and listening are
多少人看着、听着，都
like I wish my partner whether they're
希望我的伴侣，无论是正在
dating or my partner of 20 years would
约会的还是已经在一起20年的伴侣，都能主动
come to me and say can we sit down and
来找我说“我们能坐下来
talk about money but the part of that is
谈谈钱吗？”。但说实话，
is shameful about financial situation
谈论财务状况确实让人感到羞耻。
yes if I run it back 10 years just over
是的，如果我把时间倒回到10年前，也就是
10 years ago I was living in an area
10多年前，我住在拉什霍尔姆（Rush Holm）一个
called um Rush Holm I was in a
叫拉什霍尔姆的地方，和
shared house with living with some um a
几个合法
few people who had come to the UK
来到英国的人合租房子。
in my room I was in a single bed didn't
我的房间里没有地毯，睡的是单人床，
have duvet or bed sheets or anything and
没有被子、床单什么的。
every day I woke up and thought to
每天早上醒来，
myself how am I going to eat today so
我都会想今天吃什么，所以
I'd find different ways to find food at
我会想方设法找吃的。
the same time I was dating this girl
与此同时，我正在和一个叫露比的女孩约会。
called Ruby this girl called Ruby had no
露比根本不
idea she'd never seen where I lived she
知道我住在哪里，
wasn't aware that I was looking behind
也不知道我会在
uh Sofas in takeaways for pound coins
外卖店的沙发后面翻找一英镑的硬币。我绝对
there is no possibility in the world
不可能
that I would have ever told Ruby the
告诉露比我的
financial situation I was in yeah I like
经济状况。是的，
so I don't know what to do in that
我不知道在这种
situation and I'm sure I'm sure I would
情况下该怎么办。我敢肯定，
listening right now don't want to tell
现在正在听的人中，可能有30%的人不想告诉
their partner their financial situation
伴侣自己的经济状况，
because they're deeply embarrassed still
因为他们感到非常尴尬，甚至
shameful to the point that they think
羞于启齿，以至于他们觉得
be less attracted to them if they really
如果伴侣知道真相，可能会离开他们，或者对他们失去兴趣。
knew the truth I totally agree I totally
我完全
agree it's crazy how much shame we have
同意，我们竟然对金钱如此羞耻，这真是太疯狂了。无论是年轻
around money and it's uh a young guy not
小伙子缺钱，还是
having enough it's um a young woman who
年轻女孩
has $188,000 of credit card debt it's
背负18.8万美元的信用卡债务，各种情况都有。这就是
all over the Spectrum that's the second
第二
point which
点：
is if you want to talk about money talk
如果你想谈钱，那就谈
about money don't wait for your partner
钱，不要等着你的伴侣先说。
to do it bring it up yourself even if
即使
you feel embarrassed or ashamed okay if
你感到尴尬或羞愧，也要勇敢面对。如果
you're planning to make a life with this
你打算和
partner you got to be able to talk about
伴侣共度一生，就必须能够坦诚地谈论
this because you're going to be talking
这些，因为在你们的人生中，你们还会谈论
about a lot of other personal sensitive
很多其他敏感的个人
things over the course of your life the
话题。其次，还有什么比
attractive than somebody saying you know
有人坦诚地说：“你知道吗，
when I was in my
我
20s I moved to the city I spent a lot of
二十多岁的时候搬到了城里，花了很多
money going out and I wasn't super
钱出去玩，而且不太
responsible I racked up a lot of credit
负责任，欠了很多
card debt I've paid it down from 18,000
信用卡债。我已经从18000美元还到了
to 6,000 it's going to be paid off next
6000美元，
year and I just know that I'm never
明年就能还清了。我知道我再也不会重蹈覆辙了。”更有吸引力呢？
again oh my God someone who acknowledges
天哪，一个能够坦然承认
what they did has a good reason for it
自己过去行为的人，不仅有充分的理由，
and then most importantly has a plan
而且最重要的是，还有计划，这简直太有吸引力了。
huge turn on so what I'm begging all of
所以我恳请大家
us to do is to realize just because you
明白，
have more or less money does not make
金钱多少并不能决定一个
you a better or worse person I want to
人的好坏。我想
take shame away because we all have
消除羞耻感，因为我们每个人都有一些羞于启齿的事情，
something that we are ashamed of but not
但如果不去
talking about it and putting it in the
谈论，而是把它们藏在
corner in the darkness that doesn't
心底，那就太可惜了。 黑暗并不能解决
solve it that's why I love talking about
问题，这就是为什么我喜欢谈论那些
the most taboo of taboo subjects money
最禁忌的话题：金钱、性别、婚前协议、
gender prenups dating these are things
约会等等。这些都是
that nobody's talking about so when you
没人谈论的话题。所以，当你
hear couples on the podcast and they're
在播客里听到一些夫妻说他们
talking about being married for 15 years
结婚15年了，却
and they've never actually had one
从未真正
conversation about money I want you and
谈过钱的时候，我希望你和
everyone watching to be inspired because
所有观众都能受到启发，因为有些
stuff doesn't have to be shameful and
事情不必感到羞耻，也
doesn't have to be kept in the dark
不必隐瞒。那么，你对婚前协议有什么看法呢？
do you think they are a good thing for
你认为它对
all couples do you think all couples
所有夫妻都有好处吗？你认为所有夫妻都应该签婚前协议吗？
should initiate a prenup no no not all
不，并非所有夫妻都应该签。
couples there are some couples who
有些夫妻
should have one my wife and I have one
应该签，我和我妻子就签了。
so we went through this process and um
我们经历了这个过程。嗯，
who should get a prup is if one or both
哪些人应该签婚前协议呢？如果夫妻一方或双方在
premarital assets to the marriage
婚前拥有大量资产，也就是说，
meaning before they get married they
他们在结婚前
have a large Investment Portfolio a
拥有庞大的投资组合、
business rental property or a house like
企业、出租房产或房子。像
you should have AE up but most people
你这样的人应该签婚前协议，但大多数人
should not because when most people get
不应该签，因为大多数人在
married they don't have substantial
结婚时并没有大量的
assets what if your partner turns around
资产。如果你的伴侣突然反悔，
if I turn to my partner say babe ra told
如果我突然对我的伴侣说…… 宝贝拉让
me to go get a prenup yeah and she goes
我去签婚前协议，是啊，她当时就说
absolutely not well that's not a good
绝对不行，这
introduction I wouldn't say that
开场白太糟糕了。我不会这么说，
although I don't mind if you throw me
虽然我不介意你把我
under the bus oh this guy raid he said
出卖。哦，这个叫雷德的家伙说
this thing fine how to bring it up is an
这事儿，好吧，怎么开口是一门
art so when I was um deciding on a
艺术。所以，当我决定要不要签
prenup I asked for lots of advice from
婚前协议的时候，我问了
lots of friends and um some of the
很多朋友的意见，但是网上的一些
advice out there especially online is
建议，尤其是网上的，
not great um one of the most common
并不怎么样。最常见的
pieces of advice is blame it on your
建议之一就是把责任推给你的
lawyer I'm like get real you're about to
律师。我就想，醒醒吧，你马上就要
build a life with your partner and you
和你的伴侣共建未来了，难道在
can't be honest about this thing this in
这件事上不能坦诚相待吗？从
the grand scheme is a minor topic so
长远来看，这只是个小问题。所以
I'll tell you exactly what I said to my
我告诉你我是怎么跟我
wife we sat down and um we I said uh I
老婆说的，我们坐下来，我说，我
want to talk to you about something um
想跟你谈谈。
you know that because of how long I've
你知道，因为我
been in business I've been very lucky
做生意这么多年了，我很幸运，也很有福气。
I've been fortunate I worked hard I've
我努力工作，一手
built this business up and I'm really
创建了这个事业，我为自己取得的成就
proud of what I've accomplished and
和
saved and you also know my lifestyle I
积累的财富感到非常自豪。你也知道我的生活方式……
don't drive around in a Lamborghini uh I
别开兰博基尼到处跑，嗯，我
like to travel I like to wear nice
喜欢旅行，喜欢穿漂亮的
clothes and I like to save money and
衣服，也喜欢存钱。
it's important to me that as we are
对我来说，随着我们
getting closer in our relationship to
关系越来越亲密，离
getting married that we talk about a
结婚越来越近，谈谈婚前协议很重要。我当时心跳
prenup and my heart was p pounding I had
加速，因为我已经
planned it I had thought about it I had
计划好了，也考虑过，还跟
talked to so many people what I knew is
很多人聊过。我知道我
I wanted to take responsibility it's not
想承担责任，不是
some lawyer that wants it it's me it's
哪个律师想签，是我自己想签。这
important to me I wanted to bring up the
对我来说很重要，我想提出这个
topic and I wanted to reassure my wife
话题，也想让我妻子放心，
when we get married into someone who's
结婚后我不会一夜之间变成一个挥霍我们
blowing all of our money it's just
所有积蓄的人。这很
important because of the business that I
重要，因为我一手
built in her response I was like
建立的事业。我当时想，
like how is she going to respond because
她会怎么回应呢？因为
bringing up a prenup is very
提起婚前协议总是让人很
fraught she's the best she said okay I
紧张。她人很好，她说：“好吧，我
wasn't expecting that but I'm willing to
没想到她会这么说，但我愿意
learn more about it that's as good of a
了解更多。” 这已经是
response as I could have hoped so we
我所能期待的最好的回应了。于是我们
started the series of conversations we
开始了一系列的讨论。我们
both had lawyers it was going well at
各自都有律师，一开始进展顺利，
first until it wasn't and we were
直到…… 当时我们
talking about numbers that to me seemed
聊的都是些在我看来
astronomical I started to feel resentful
天文数字般的数字，我开始感到不满。她觉得我没听
she didn't feel listened to she didn't
进去，没被我理解，
feel heard she started to feel resentful
她开始感到不满。
and these conversations were were like
这些对话非常
so difficult I would say they were some
艰难，可以说是
our relationship at one point she said
我们关系中最艰难的几次对话之一。有一次，她说
we should go see a therapist because
我们应该去看心理咨询师，因为
these conversations are not good and I
这样的对话不好。我说
was like you're right so we went to see
你说得对，所以我们就去看了心理
a therapist we sat in that therapist
咨询师。我们坐在咨询师的
office I still remember therapist asked
办公室里，我还记得咨询师问了
us a bunch of questions including how do
我们很多问题，包括
you see money and she turned to me I was
你们对金钱的看法等等。 她转向我，我
an obvious question then she turns to my
问她：“我该如何看待金钱的增长？”我眼前仿佛浮现出无数数字，我内心的优化者立刻想到了“72法则”。这问题太显而易见了，简直是天方夜谭。然后她转向我
wife how do you see money and she said
妻子，问她：“你如何看待金钱？”妻子回答说：“
safety so what sa safety to me that was
安全。”对我来说，“安全”是什么意思？这
like saying charcoal like the two words
就像说“木炭”一样，这两个词根本
don't relate at
不搭边。
all but it started us on A New Path of
但这开启了我们看待
realizing that we were seeing money
金钱的新篇章，让我们意识到彼此对金钱的看法
completely differently me and that was
截然不同。正是在那时，
exactly when I realized I wish there
我意识到，我希望有
were other couples talking about money
更多夫妻能够私下里坦诚地谈论金钱。
from behind closed doors that exactly
这正是
was the Genesis of me doing my podcast
我制作播客
and my Netflix show to show people not
和Net​​flix节目的初衷，我想让人们看到
just tell them but to show them how real
真实的
couples deal with money what was the
夫妻是如何处理金钱的，而不仅仅是空谈。
resistance between you two in sort of
你们之间的阻力是什么？
more specific terms she she wanted a
更具体地说，她想要的是一种与
you wanted yeah the terms are are super
你想要的不同安排。是的，婚前协议的条款非常
technical in prenups it's um so with a
专业。
prenup you have a variety of different
婚前协议包含各种不同的
rules or technicalities which would be
规则或细节，比如：
like what if you separate in 6 months
如果你们6个月后分居怎么办？
what if you separate in 25 years but
如果你们25年后分居，但
there are children involved who gets the
有孩子怎么办？房子归谁？
house what if you have a house what if
如果你有一套房子怎么办？如果
you have two houses what if you have
你有两套房子怎么办？如果你们
this much in your joint investment but
共同投资有这么多钱，但
each of you has this much in individual
你们每个人的个人
investment and so what happens is it's
投资又有多少呢？所以问题
not even just the numbers themselves
不仅仅在于数字本身，还在于整个
it's the fact that the process is set up
流程被设计
to be adversarial mhm so they have a
成对抗性的。嗯，所以他们有
lawyer we have a lawyer we're
律师，我们也有律师，我们在
comes to this topic when normally you're
讨论这个话题时都得通过律师沟通，而通常情况下，你
just talking to your fiance or your
只需要和你的未婚夫或女朋友谈谈就行了。和
managing the lawyers see the lawyers
律师沟通也是一门艺术。律师当然
want there's nothing bad we had great
想要什么，这没什么不好，我们的
lawyers I'm happy with them but lawyers
律师很棒，我很满意，但律师的
job is to look over every freaking
职责是审查每一个可能出现的
contingency and make sure that nothing
情况，确保没有任何遗漏。
is left a chance and I think a good
我认为，
reminder for anyone considering a prenup
对于任何考虑婚前协议的人来说，一个很好的提醒
is to remember you manage your lawyers
是：你要管理你的律师，
and your job is to come to an agreement
你的职责是
with your partner for the rest of your
与你的伴侣达成终身协议。
life so sometimes you can be generous
所以，有时候你可以宽容一些，
you can be willing to let up on a few
愿意在某些方面做出让步，
things here and there as long as you are
只要你
looking at the Northstar we're going to
着眼于最终目标——我们将永远在一起——
be together we want these premarital
我们希望这些婚前
assets to be protected and in case
财产得到保护。 万一出了
something goes wrong we both want to
什么问题，我们都希望
feel good about what the arrangement is
对目前的安排感到满意。
that you will break up if you look at
如果你看看
the marriage statistics so well those
婚姻统计数据，就会发现有大约60%的概率会分手。当然，这些
statistics are a little skewed that
统计数据有点偏差，因为它们
includes second marriages that also
包含了再婚，也
includes all different socioeconomic all
包含了各种社会经济地位的
everybody else if you break it down for
人。如果你细分一下，比如只看
example just by having a bachelor's
拥有学士学位，
degree or certainly an advanced degree
或者更高学位的人，那么
that goes way down first marriage goes
第一次结婚的概率就会大大降低。
down and in fact the divorce rate has
事实上，离婚率几
been decreasing for decades so this 50
十年来一直在下降。所以，这个被
60% thing that's kind of tossed around
反复提及的50%或60%的说法
not quite accurate but whatever the
并不完全准确。但无论
statistic is what's more important is if
统计数据如何，更重要的是，
you should always think about how can
你应该始终思考事情如何才能
things go right and also how can they go
顺利进行，以及可能出现哪些问题。
wrong and I think with money A lot of
我认为在金钱方面，
times uh we only think about one or the
我们很多时候只考虑其中一方面。
other we buy a house never asking
我们买房从来不会问
ourselves like what if one of us loses
自己，如果其中一方失业怎么办？
our job and we get married without ever
我们结婚从来不会
asking like what if we separate so you
考虑，如果分手怎么办？所以，你
want to be able to play both what
需要能够兼顾两者：
happens if things go right incredibly
如果一切顺利，会发生什么？
right and what happens if things go
如果出了问题，又会发生什么？
wrong let's make a plan what are the
让我们制定一个计划，还有
other red flags then we mentioned the
哪些危险信号？ 然后我们提到了
first being they don't want to talk
第一点，那就是他们不想谈
about money ah um they have a money guy
钱。嗯，他们有个“理财顾问”。“
a money guy is so common everybody talks
理财顾问”这个词很常见，每个人都在谈论它。
about I have this money guy your money
我也有个“理财顾问”，你的“理财
guy is probably uh whole life in
顾问”可能就是个终身
insurance salesman charging you 1.25%
寿险推销员，按资产管理规模（AUM）收取1.25%的费用。
AUM let me explain what that means so
让我解释一下这意味着什么。
many people in America do not want to
很多美国人不想
learn the basics of money and so they
学习基本的理财知识，所以他们就
hire a financial adviser now I don't
雇佣理财顾问。我并不
have anything against financial advisors
反对理财顾问，
in general but a money guy that they're
但他们
typically referring to is someone who
通常所说的“理财顾问”是
charges them a percentage of their
指按
assets so if I have a $100,000 portfolio
资产百分比收费的人。比如说，如果我有一个10万美元的投资组合，
they'll charge or let's say a million
他们会收取费用；或者假设我的投资
dollar portfolio I might be paying 1% 1%
组合有100万美元，我可能要支付1%的费用。1%
doesn't sound like a lot but if you
听起来不多，但如果你仔细
actually run the math you will pay about
算算，
28% of your lifetime investment returns
你一生投资收益的28%左右都会被收取
in fees that's not $10 or $100 that's
费用。这可不是10美元或100美元，而是几万美元，
tens of thousands or sometimes hundreds
有时甚至是几
of thousands of dollars so it's a red
十万美元。所以，
flag if someone has an advisor that
如果有人雇佣的顾问按
they're paying a percentage based fee to
百分比收费，那就很危险了。
I would much rather you pay an hourly or
我宁愿你支付…… 按小时、按
project or that type of fee too
项目收费或者其他类似的收费方式也行，
okay um they're
嗯，他们很
cheap I can help a lot of people but I
抠门。我能帮很多人，但我
can't help cheap cheap
帮不了抠门的人。抠门
is cost is the first and last thing they
就是成本，他们
always consider so you might come home
总是把成本放在第一位，最后才考虑。所以你可能回家后高兴地说：“天哪，
you're so happy oh my gosh look at this
看看
beautiful thing I got for the kids how
我给孩子们买的这个漂亮东西，
much was that and it just sucks the life
多少钱啊？”结果它让
out of every room cheap people are
每个房间都失去了生气。抠门的人
obsessed with cost cheap people rarely
对成本着迷，他们很少
recognize the effect they are having on
意识到自己对
their loved ones and cheap people
亲人的影响，而且他们
find it very very difficult to change
很难改变，
they don't want to change they actually
他们不想改变，他们甚至会重新
reinterpret their behavior and call it a
解释自己的行为，称之为
virtue oh I'm not that I don't need that
美德。“哦，我不是说我不需要那种
fancy wine I'm perfectly happy with this
名贵的酒，我对这个很满意。”
well what if your partner wants one
可是如果你的伴侣想喝一
glass of wine they seem like a miserable
杯酒怎么办？他们看起来真是一群可怜虫。是
group yeah I don't like cheap people I
啊，我不喜欢抠门的人，我
don't like cheap people I don't like
不喜欢抠门的人，我不喜欢
cheap tippers and their Partners don't
小费给得少的人，他们的伴侣也不
like them so it's it's one I'm not
喜欢他们。所以，我不是
saying everybody has to go out and spend
说每个人都必须出去花
a million dollars but you got to use
一百万美元，但你必须用
money to live your rich life the point
钱来过上富裕的生活，
of money is not to just hoard it and
金钱的意义在于…… 不是要把钱囤起来，而是要学会
save it that's why when you create a
理财。所以，当你制定一个
rich life Vision you ask yourself what
富足的生活愿景时，你要问问自己：哪些方面值得挥霍，
do we want to spend extravagantly on not
不是
just a little bit but extravagantly and
一点点，而是要挥霍；
what do we want to cut cost mercilessly
哪些方面又需要毫不留情地削减开支。
on you have to be able to play different
你必须像演奏交响乐一样，能够灵活运用不同的
notes like you're in a symphony if your
元素。如果你
only note is spend less that's a
唯一的“音符”就是“少花钱”，那你的
miserable existence are there any more
生活将会非常痛苦。还有其他需要注意的
red flags I want to go into why people
危险信号吗？我想探讨一下人们为什么会
and where they develop these
以及在哪里
relationships with money but are there
与金钱建立起这种关系，但还有其他一些
that we should be looking for well if
值得关注的突出危险信号吗？
they if they follow Robert kosaki that's
如果他们追随罗伯特·科萨基（Robert Kosaki），那绝对是一个
a huge red flag I mean the guy
巨大的危险信号。我的意思是，
once Robert kosaki wrote this uh
罗伯特·科萨基曾经写过一本
well-known personal finance book and the
非常著名的个人理财书籍，但他
guy has really lost it in the last few
最近
years he literally I'm not joking he
几年真的疯了。他真的——我没开玩笑——
literally told people the best
告诉人们最好的
investment you can have is a can of
投资就是一罐
tuna I'm not joking and I replied to him
金枪鱼。我没开玩笑。我回复他说：“
Robert I sold everything in my portfolio
罗伯特，我卖掉了我投资组合里的所有东西，
and bought 3 million cans of tuna um is
买了300万罐金枪鱼。”
this a good investment but sadly I never
这难道不是…… 投资不错，可惜我一直没
heard back so beware of Beware of
收到回复。所以要提防
charlatans let me put it that way
骗子。这么说吧，
personal finance and money is filled
个人理财和金钱领域充斥
with people who will promise you get
着各种承诺让你
rich quick who will tell you that the
快速致富、危言耸听的人。说到
money we want to be balanced we want to
金钱，我们想要的是平衡，想要
have fun we want to be have a healthy
享受生活，想要
relationship with money it's very
和金钱建立健康的关系。这和
similar to Fitness lots of people making
健身很像，很多人都会做出各种
promises you want to find the people who
承诺。你要找到的是那些能给
are giving you long-term advice you know
你提供长期建议的人。你知道
these cheap people that you mentioned
你提到的那些抠门的人吗？
mhm and you know any of them I a couple
嗯，你认识他们吗？我
come to mind tell tell the camera who
脑海里立刻浮现出几个例子，现在就告诉镜头
they are right now so we know who are
他们是谁。所以我们知道谁是
these cheap people they also fit into
这些抠门的人了。根据我的经验，他们也属于“
the category of the Warriors in my
战士”这一类。
experience so someone who's a bit of a
所以，一个有点“
warrior can also be quite quite cheap
战士”气质的人也可能非常抠门。
and I was just wondering in the hundreds
我只是好奇，在
of couples that you've sat down with an
你
interviewed does there tend to be a
采访过的数百对夫妇中，他们的节俭和抠门是否有一个共同的
origin story which links to their Friv
起源故事？是的，好的。
when I talk to people um I asked them
每当我和人们交谈时，我都会问他们：
what do you remember your parents saying
你记得你的父母是怎么说的吗？ 孩子们从小就经常谈
about money when you grew up always and
钱，
they'll tell me they are very conversant
他们会告诉我他们对金钱非常了解，
they remember and usually the parents
他们记得很清楚。通常父母会
said stuff like we can't afford it and
说些类似“我们买不起”、“
uh money doesn't grow on trees we don't
钱又不是天上掉下来的”、“我们
talk about money in this family these
家不谈钱”之
are the type of things that people said
类的话。
but you will often find um usually when
但你会发现，通常到了
teenagers when there's something really
青少年时期，如果
tragic that happens and it's of often
发生一些非常不幸的事情，比如
that um Dad lost his job and that meant
父亲失业，导致家庭
socioeconomically often they had a big
经济状况彻底改变，他们可能原本住着大
house they had to really like shift into
房子，不得不搬到
Grandma's apartment that kind of thing
奶奶家住，这种事情会对
that affects people in a huge way now it
人们产生巨大的影响。这种影响通常有
affects people in one of two ways and
两种，而且
you cannot predict how some people go
你无法预测。有些人会说：“
I'm never going to let that happen to me
我绝不会让这种事发生在我身上，
therefore I'm going to have a high
所以我要保持高
savings rate I'm going to invest I'm
储蓄率，我要投资，我要
going to start a business and they
创业。”他们会
develop a really healthy relationship
建立起非常健康的金钱观。而
with money others go the Direction
另一些人则会像
you're suggesting which is they become
你所说的那样，变得
incredibly cheap incredibly worried
极其吝啬，
about money anxiety is common and they
对金钱极度焦虑。这种焦虑很常见，他们
often do not see the connection at all
往往根本意识不到其中的联系，
until I point it out to them and when
直到我指出来。当你和他们
you talk about making this Rich Life
谈论金钱时，你会发现他们往往难以理解。 关于共同打造“富足人生”
vision together what exactly does that
愿景，这究竟
mean we start off in the book just
意味着什么？我们在书中首先要
talking about let's have our first
谈谈，让我们进行第一次
positive conversation about money okay
关于金钱的积极对话。
you have to remember most people have
你要记住，大多数人
never had a positive conversation about
从未进行过关于金钱的积极对话。
money money is the the only way it comes
金钱对他们来说，唯一的话题就是“
up is why did you spend that much at the
你上周为什么在加油站花了那么多钱？”仅此而已。
gas station last week that's it so we
所以我们首先
start off by just saying I give him an
要给他一个
agenda literally an agenda you can read
议程，你可以
off these words and start it off it's
照着念，然后开始。
like why this is going to be awesome
比如，为什么这会很棒？这是
here's how I feel about money today how
我今天对金钱的感受，你觉得呢？这是我
do you feel here's how I want to feel
想要对
about money how about you high five I
金钱的感受，你觉得呢？击掌！我
love you we're good that's it part of
爱你！我们很好！就是这样。
having conversations about money
关于金钱的对话，其
is this philosophy of declare Victory
理念是“宣告胜利，
and go home you don't need to talk about
然后回家”。你不需要
it all at once make it short make it fun
一次性谈完所有内容，要简短，要有趣，
and at the end always say I love you
最后一定要说“我爱你”。就这样，
that's it over time you're going to
随着时间的推移，你会将
associate talking about money with
谈论金钱与
positivity and that's what we want when
积极的心态联系起来，而这正是我们
it comes to a rich life Vision this is
实现“富足人生”愿景的目标。这才是
where it's really fun so I have some
真正有趣的地方，所以我准备了一些
fill in the blanks um where you fill it
填空题。 你先填上“
in like I wish we spent more money on
我希望我们在某方面多花点钱”，
and then you fill it in I think we could
然后填上“我觉得我们可以在某方面
probably cut back on and then you fill
减少开支”，再填上“我觉得我们可以在某方面减少开支”，
it in then you compare your notes my
然后你们互相比较。我和我
wife and I did this really fun exercise
妻子做了一个非常有趣的练习，
which I would encourage everyone to do
我鼓励大家都去做，那
and it is the 10-year bucket list so
就是“十年愿望清单”。
imagine you sit down with your partner
想象一下，你和你的伴侣坐下来，
and you go let's each take a piece of
你们各自拿一张
paper write down what would make the
纸，写下
next 10 years incredibly Rich meaningful
接下来的十年里，什么事情会让未来十年变得无比充实、意义非凡，
to to me and to us so you write it down
对我和我们来说都意义重大。你们写下来，
and then you compare notes this is
然后互相比较。我们就是这么做的。
exactly what we did and you get excited
你会很兴奋，比如“
you oh you want to learn Spanish amazing
哦，你想学西班牙语，太棒了！你想
do you want to do it online or do you
在线学习还是
want to go to Mexico City oh you want to
去墨西哥城？”或者“哦，你想去
go skydiving ah that one's not for me
跳伞，啊，这个不适合我，
but I'll meet you at the ground right
但我会在地面等你，好吗？玩得开心！”
have fun and you just get excited you
你们都很兴奋，互相
encourage the other person and then you
鼓励，然后
find one that you both want to do that's
找到一个你们都想做、
meaningful for both of you so maybe it
对你们都有意义的事情。比如，
is we want to um create an art studio in
我们想在车库里建一个艺术工作室，太棒了！
the garage love it maybe it is we want
或者我们想在
point in the next 10 years okay great
未来的某个时候环游世界。 十年，太好了！
the difference with this exercise is
这个练习的不同之处在于，
you're actually going to make it happen
你真的要把它变成现实。
so right there on the spot you estimate
所以，当场估算一下
how much it would cost take five minutes
大概需要多少钱，五分钟就够了，别超过五分钟，
estimate it within 80% like that decide
估算结果最好在80%以内。然后决定
when you want to do it maybe if there's
你想什么时候做，比如如果有
kids involved you're going to want to go
孩子的话，你想
in summer winter Etc and then all you do
在夏天、冬天等等。接下来，你只需
is take the rough amount divide it by
要把大概的金额除以
the number of months and that's how you
月份，就能
know how much you have to save for it we
知道你需要存多少钱了。我们
did this and for us what was really
做了这个练习，对我们来说，真正
meaningful is to have a 10year wedding
有意义的是庆祝结婚十周年。
anniversary so we know where we want to
所以我们知道想在哪里庆祝，
do it we know the exact place we know
知道具体地点，知道
all the friends and family want to have
所有想和
with us and we knew when it was going to
我们一起庆祝的亲朋好友，也知道什么时候庆祝。
happen so we we had a funny experience
我们经历了一件很有趣的事，
because we each sat down and estimated
因为我们各自坐下来估算
the cost and I think the number I picked
费用，我记得我估算的数字好像是
than hers and in those cases I say go
她估算的三倍。在这种情况下，我建议选择
with the bigger number okay it helps you
较大的数字。这能帮助你把
dream a little bigger if you can't save
梦想做得更大一些。如果你每个月存不了
that much money per month that's okay
那么多钱，也没关系，
shrink the dream a little bit right
稍微缩小一下梦想的
narrow the scope or maybe extend it a
范围。 或许可以稍微延长一下期限，
little longer until you have to do it
直到不得不付账为止。
but suddenly every single month when you
但突然间，每个月
sit down and talk about money it's like
坐下来谈钱的时候，就像玩
a video game you're like oh we're 3%
电子游戏一样，你会想：哦，我们离
closer to that goal that is how you
目标又近了3%！这就是你
start to build a vision for money and
开始建立理财愿景并
have fun along the way and do you
享受过程的方式。
subscribe to this idea that you should
你是否认同应该有
have like a joint bank account and then
一个联名账户，然后再
separate bank accounts or because right
各自开一个账户？因为
now I just have my bank account and how
我现在只有我自己的银行账户。这种方式
does it work how does it work for you so
对你来说行得通吗？
do you just you just pay for most things
你是不是大部分开销都自己付？
I have to give context on what my
我得先介绍一下我的
partner's like she really doesn't care
伴侣，她真的不在乎
about material things so she's avoider
物质的东西，她是个回避型人格。
she just doesn't she doesn't care about
她不在乎我们坐的是头等舱
whether we fly first class or economy
还是经济舱，
she doesn't care about if we stay in
不在乎我们住的是
that hotel or this hotel right she
这家酒店还是那家酒店，不在乎
doesn't care if we stay in the 70th
我们住的是70层的顶层
floor Penthouse we live there or or if
公寓还是
she stays in a studio she doesn't care
她自己住的单间公寓。她不在乎什么？她只在乎
quality time with me she likes having
和我共度的美好时光。她喜欢
nice experiences she likes going to
美好的体验，喜欢去不同的
places doesn't care how she gets there
地方，不在乎她如何……
or where she stays she likes traveling
她喜欢旅行
and exploring and she likes her simple
和探索，也喜欢简单的
thing she's a very simple person if I
生活，她是个很简单的人。如果我
didn't get her birthday present or
没给她准备生日礼物、
Valentine's Day present or Christmas
情人节礼物或圣诞
present or if I just made her a
礼物，或者每年只给她做一本
scrapbook every year she'll be thrilled
剪贴簿，她也会很开心。
okay so I am the one that wants the
好吧，所以我是那个想要
nicer you want the okay I'm the same I'm
更好的人，你想要更好的。好吧，我们俩差不多，
the same to to a large extent but we
很大程度上一样。但是，
have a like we you know life it costs
你知道，生活需要
money so
花钱，所以
um I pay for most things okay and you're
大部分东西都是我付的。好吧，你觉得这样可以吗？没问题，对吧？是的，
cool with that it's fine right yeah I've
我
always been cool with it okay cool so
一直都觉得可以。好吧，太好了。所以
I'm particularly cool with it because
我特别觉得可以，因为
she doesn't care right right does that
她不在乎，对吧？这样说得通吗？是的，这样说得通，所以她
make sense yes it makes there's no
不会心生
resentment because she doesn't care I'm
怨恨，因为她不在乎。是我
the one that's making sure she travels
确保她
this way yeah I have to intervene and I
这样旅行的。是的，我必须介入，我
have to fight to make sure that her
必须争取，确保她的
plane ticket is booked here or that the
机票订好了，或者
hotel she's staying in isn't going to be
她住的酒店不会有
dangerous I've got so many stories of
危险。我有很多
her booking it herself and then me
她自己订票，然后我
having to rescue her because it's super
不得不去救她的故事。 这超级
dangerous yeah so so you and I have a
危险，是啊。所以，你我之间有种
similar um Dynamic at least in this way
相似的……嗯，至少在这方面是这样。
um I think my wife does have her money
我觉得我老婆也有她自己的“金钱
dials money dials are the things you
偏好”，就是她
love to spend money on and you can turn
喜欢花钱的地方，而且你可以把
that dial up but when we met she was not
这个偏好调高。但我们刚认识的时候，她
into hotels at all I'm a hotel guy I
对酒店一点兴趣都没有。我可是个酒店控，我
love hotels and so we had to have some
爱酒店。所以一开始我们不得不好好
conversations at first I'm just like oh
聊聊。我当时就说，哦，当然是
yeah like of course I'm paying and then
我付钱啦。后来
when we merged our finances which I
我们合并了财务，我
recommend couples do well suddenly it's
建议情侣们都这么做。突然之间，这
not my money it's our money yeah and so
不再是我的钱，而是我们的钱了。所以
now we are forced to talk about that
现在我们不得不讨论这些
stuff and come up with a way like she's
事情，想办法解决。比如，她说她
like I don't need to stay there and like
不需要住那里，她
personally I don't really think it's
个人觉得那不值这个价。
worth it for our money and I'm like well
我就说，
like have you seen have you seen the
你见过那家酒店的
suite at this place and do you know what
套房吗？你知道
type of wood they use and that she
他们用的是什么木材吗？她根本
doesn't care so so how does that work
不在乎。所以，这到底是怎么回事？
you said you merge your finances when
你说你们合并了财务，你说合并
you say you merge your finances do you
财务是
mean you're paying into the same bank
指把钱存到同一个银行
account correct so and this is what I
账户里，对吧？ 我
recommend for most for for almost all
建议大多数
couples um you take your paychecks or if
情侣都这样做：你们各自领取工资，或者如果
you're we're both business owners you
你们都是企业主，就把
take whatever money comes in put it in
所有收入都存入
the joint checking account that joint
联名支票账户。这个
checking account then pays a variety of
账户会支付各种
different accounts it pays our joint
不同的账单，比如我们的共同
expenses like our rent and if we eat out
开支，像房租，以及我们外出就餐的账单。此外，
joint checking to her individual
联名账户里的钱也会转到她的个人
checking and individual savings which
支票账户和个人储蓄账户，
she has her money no questions asked if
她可以自由支配自己的钱，无需任何询问。如果
she wants to spend it on something like
她想把钱花在自己喜欢的东西上，比如
she loves
她喜欢的
self-care what am I going to ask it's
自我护理，我还能问什么呢？那是
her money it also sends some money over
她的钱。账户里也会有一部分钱转给
to me that's no questions asked money
我，这部分钱也是我自由支配的，无需任何询问。是的，
came in from us two together is
我们两个人的收入都会
processed in the joint checking account
存入联名支票
account and an amount goes to each of us
账户，然后按比例分配给我们每个人，金额
the same amount goes to both of you good
相同。问得好，
question it could be the same 50/50 I
可以是50/50，我
think is actually great but once in a
觉得这样很好。但
while if you have somebody who's earning
偶尔，如果一方的收入是另一方的
like let's say 10 times more okay you
十倍，你们
may decide to make it proportional right
可以考虑按比例分配，
so like one the higher earning partner
比如收入较高的一方可以获得
might get more because imagine just for
更多。 因为试想一下，
argument sake imagine you're earning a
假设你每月收入一
million dollars a month easy
百万美元（这很容易
math and um suddenly you're getting like
算），然后突然间，你
$22,000 a month for guilt fre spending
每月还能拿到2.2万美元的“无愧疚消费金”，
you're like um what the hell this this
你肯定会想：这到底是怎么回事？这根本说不通。
doesn't make sense usually partners are
通常伴侣们
totally cool with that but I will tell
对此都完全没意见，但我得告诉
you this I used to be on the
你，我以前也信奉
proportionality train meaning
比例原则，认为
everything's proportional Etc my wife
所有消费都要成比例等等。我和我妻子这样
and I did this for many
做了很多
years it's really complicated it gets
年，这真的很复杂，非常非常
really really complicated and what's
复杂。
more important is you want to set your
更重要的是，你要设置好
accounts up so that they drive the right
账户，让它们引导正确的
Behavior just like when you hire people
行为，就像你招聘员工时，要
you set the right incentives to drive
设定合适的激励机制来引导正确的行为一样。
the right Behavior when our moneyy was
以前我们的财务是
separate and we were doing all this
分开的，我们做着各种
proportionality calculation all these
比例计算，设置了各种
different accounts we didn't see the
不同的账户，我们并不觉得这些钱是属于我们
money as ours now all the money goes
的。现在所有的钱都进了同一个账户，它就是属于
into that pot it's ours so we sit down
我们的了。所以我们
every month we look at our numbers and
每个月都会坐下来，看看账目，然后思考：
we go what's worth it do we care about
哪些东西值得花？我们真的喜欢
this hotel do we care about that etc etc
这家酒店吗？我们喜欢那家酒店吗？等等等等。
we really love that let's keep spending
我们真的很喜欢，那就继续花在这些地方，想
on that and find a way to do that it's
办法继续花下去。这都是
about us and of course we have our own
为了我们自己。 当然，我们每个人都有自己的
individual money so why didn't you just
收入，所以为什么不直接把
the money coming in Why didn't it just
钱存入各自的账户呢？为什么不让钱先
go to you individually and then you pay
进入你的个人账户，然后再由你
into the joint account why did you make
存入联名账户？
that's what we did at first and it
我们一开始就是这么做的，结果
became really complicated so the money
变得非常复杂。钱先
came into each of us and then we because
进入我们每个人的账户，然后因为
we each run businesses that are each
我们各自经营着生意，每个生意都有
variable we wanted it to be proportional
变动，所以我们想让比例保持一致。
well guess what if it changes every
结果呢？如果
single month we had to recalculate the
每个月都在变化，我们就得
proportionality every single quarter
每个季度重新计算比例，真是太
what a mess so we're we're literally
混乱了！所以我们实际上
calculating every 3 months and then it
每三个月就要重新计算一次，然后比例又
changes and then at the end of the year
变了，到了年底
we have to reconcile all this stuff
我们还得把所有这些账目都核对一遍。我们当时就想，
we're like what is this marriage or a
这到底是婚姻还是
freaking multi-national conglomerate so
跨国集团？所以，
vision is one of our values is fight for
我们“富足生活愿景”理念的一部分，就是追求
Simplicity fight for it because I talk
简单，坚持下去。因为我接触
to couples who have more complicated
过一些夫妻，他们的
Financial setups than we do shouldn't be
财务安排比我们复杂得多，这不应该是
the case most people's setups should be
常态。大多数人的财务安排都应该
very simple all your money comes into a
非常简单：所有的钱都先进入一个
joint checking account from there it is
联名支票账户，然后从那里转到
it pays out to individual accounts
各自的账户，
and it pays all your joint expenses your
支付你们所有的共同开支，以及你们的
life is together your rich life is
生活开支。 你们的富裕生活就是你们
together that's it we're married we're
共同的，就是这样，我们结婚了，我们
going to be married forever our future
将永远在一起，我们的未来也在一起，
is together so let's set our accounts up
所以让我们
accordingly so then if you end up
相应地设置账户。这样，如果最终
getting a divorce that joint checking
离婚，那个联名支票
account do you just split it in half or
账户是平分还是平分呢？
yeah so this is a this is a good
这是一个好
question when you are married the money
问题。结婚后，共同
that is earned is community property so
赚取的收入属于夫妻共同财产。
let's just say we put $100,000 in that
假设我们往那个支票账户里存了10万美元，如果
checking account and we were to get
我们
separated tomorrow
明天就分居了，那么平分，对吧？这很
5050 yeah that and that's reasonable
合理，对吧？
right it's community property the prenup
这是夫妻共同财产。婚前协议
is only concerned with what happened
只涉及婚前发生的事情。
marriage so you're in the camp of not
所以你属于那种不太
caring too much about the small expenses
在意小额开支的人，比如你觉得买
the coffee it's a waste of time why is
咖啡是浪费时间。为什么说是
it a waste of time because the they are
浪费时间呢？因为一杯咖啡才
$3 questions if you actually add it up
3美元。如果你真的算算它
how much they actually cost you it's
实际花费了你多少钱，
actually not that much it's the simple
其实并没有那么多。这是
joy that you enjoy in the morning and
你早上享受到的简单快乐。
you could spend your entire life
你可以花一辈子
agonizing over buying a coffee but when
纠结买咖啡这件事，但当
I ask people okay so you stopped buying
我问别人“你一个月没买
coffee for a month how'd you feel they
咖啡感觉怎么样？”时，他们会说“
go oh I felt okay I go what' you do with
哦，我……” 感觉还不错，我就问他们：“你
the money you saved they go I don't know
省下的钱怎么用？”他们说：“不知道，都存在
it's in my checking account not only do
我的支票账户里了。”你不仅
single day to save on these tiny little
每天都要决定在这些
things you then have to properly invest
小事上省钱，而且…… 把钱好好投资，
that money and you have to do this every
而且你必须在
single day for the rest of your life
余生中每天都这样做。
what if we just got five critical
如果我们余生只需做对五个关键
decisions correct for the rest of our
决定，就
life and didn't have to worry about
不用再为
coffee why are we playing so small oh
咖啡发愁了，那该多好？为什么我们总是小打小闹？哦，我们先来
let's decide do we have enough money to
决定一下，我们有足够的钱买
buy this Saran Wrap who cares let's talk
这个保鲜膜吗？谁在乎呢？我们来谈谈
about are we investing properly do we
我们的投资是否合理？我们是否
have a a Target rate that we are doing
有目标利率？
watch this I bet you so many couples
看看这个，我敢打赌，现在正在看这个视频的很多夫妻都吵过架，比如“
arguments about why did you spend so
你为什么
much at the grocery store why can't you
在超市花那么多钱？”、“你为什么不能少给
stop spending so much on the kids and on
孩子花钱？”等等。
and on but have they ever had
但他们有没有像这样
conversations like this what is our
讨论过呢？我们的
savings rate is it 4% 6% 7% what is our
储蓄率是多少？是4%？6%？7%？我们的
investment rate is it 6% 8% whatever the
投资率是多少？是6%？8%？不管
number is Let's Make a rule that every
是多少，我们定个规矩，每年
December we increase it by
12月增加
1% if you just did that if you increase
1%。如果你刚刚这么做了，如果你提高了
your investment rate meaning the
你的投资率，也就是
percentage of your net income that you
你
invest every single month I always
每个月投资的净收入百分比，我总是
recommend people start off at 5 to 10%
建议人们从5%到10%开始。
let's say you're at six if you make a
假设你现在是6%，如果你定个
rule every December we're going to
规矩，每年12月增加1%。 我们要把
increase that by 1%
它提高1%，
it will be worth hundreds of thousands
这将为你带来数十万
of dollars to you more than all the
美元的价值，比
coffee you ever buy in your entire life
你这辈子买的所有咖啡加起来都多。
so why the hell would you focus on
所以，你为什么还要把精力放在
coffee when you can make one decision
咖啡上呢？你每年只需做一个决定，就能赚到
per year and make way more than all
比所有
those coffees combined most couples when
咖啡加起来都多的钱。大多数情侣在
they think about investing or their
考虑投资或
investment rate the only investment most
投资比例时，他们共同做的唯一投资就是买房。是啊，但这甚至都
not even an investment most people think
算不上投资。大多数人认为
renting is wasting money yeah and the
租房是浪费钱。他们的
the logic goes well if my rent is $2,000
逻辑是：如果我的房租每月2000美元
a month or £2,000 a month my mortgage is
或2000英镑，我的房贷
only going to be £2,000 a month and we
每月也只有2000英镑，
so we might as well buy a house because
所以我们还不如买房，因为
then we get to keep the asset are you
这样我们就能拥有这笔资产。你是想
trying to get me mad right now I'm
激怒我吗？我
starting to Swit just hearing this
听到这些话都开始生气了，
because you're right that's what they
因为你说得对，他们就是这么说的。我应该现在就彻底
say should I just dismantle these
驳斥这些
arguments once and for all right now
论点吗？
sure okay renting is not throwing away
好吧，租房不是浪费钱，
money just like going to a sushi
就像去寿司
restaurant is not throwing money away on
店吃寿司不是浪费钱一样，
Sushi you're paying for something you're
你付的是钱。 你从中
getting value you it's fantastic the
获得的价值很棒，
next argument they use is um you're
他们接下来的论点是：你在
paying your landlord's mortgage I go
帮房东还房贷。我会说，
okay aren't you paying the sushi owner's
好吧，那你去寿司店吃寿司的时候，不也是在帮寿司店老板还
mortgage when you go there and get sushi
房贷吗？
funny we never think about it like that
有趣的是，我们从来没这样想过，
we only think about paying the
我们只想着帮
landlord's mortgage finally we have to
房东还房贷。最后，我们必须
understand that buying a house can be a
明白，买房可能是一个
good financial decision it can be but
不错的财务决定，的确如此，但
renting and investing the difference can
租房和投资之间的差价
also be a good decision and right now in
也可能是一个不错的决定。目前，
the US in the top 50 US Metro cities it
在美国排名前50的大都市，
is cheaper to rent than to buy so let me
租房比买房更划算。让我
give you some math let's say because I
给你算笔账。假设我
lived in New York close
住在纽约
by if the rent was let's say 3,000 bucks
附近，如果租金是每月3000美元，那么
a month to own the equivalent property
拥有一套隔壁同等条件的房子
right next door would have been 6,600 a
每月就要6600美元，也就是说，仅仅
$3,600 per month more just to own so
为了拥有它，每月就要多花3600美元。
most people don't know this they don't
大多数人不知道这一点，他们没有把维护费、
taxes transaction opportunity cost they
税费、交易机会成本等隐形成本考虑进去，他们只是
simply look at a number that says uh
看到一个数字，比如
3,600 or whatever the number may be and
3600美元，或者其他什么数字，然后就…… 这是一项
they go great investment we have got to
很棒的投资，我们必须
get more sophisticated with the biggest
更理性地看待人生中最大的一笔
purchase of Our
支出。
Lives I'm just looking at some of the uh
我正在看
comments on our last conversation oh
上次谈话的一些评论，哦，
yeah what did they say it's a balancing
他们说了什么？这需要权衡。
act there's there's two groups of people
这里有两类人，
here there's a group of people who
一类人
attest to the fact that they bought a
坚信他们买了房
house and it's the single best thing
子，这是
they did yep um this person said I
他们做过的最棒的事。是的，这个人说：“我
bought a house it's the best thing I
买了房子，这是我做过的最棒的事，它
ever did it's launched my mindset and
开启了我的思维模式，为我指明了
New Direction
新的方向。”
remember that having your own space has
记住，拥有自己的空间会对你的
profound psychological impacts and can
心理产生深远的影响，并
change your life that's a good comment
能改变你的人生。这是一个很好的评论。
okay let's talk about that first I love
好的，我们先来谈谈这个。我喜欢
that comment we have to remember that
这个评论。我们必须记住，
life is not just about a spreadsheet
生活不仅仅是电子表格，
it's not so when it comes to a major
不是这样的。所以，当涉及到
purchase like a house or a car we got to
像房子或车子这样的大宗消费时，我们必须
start with the numbers okay we have to
从数字入手。好的，我们必须
start by running a buy versus rent
先计算一下买房和租房的利弊，
calculation by running an amortization
通过运行摊销
chart I have a whole bunch of stuff on
表。我有很多关于
buy versus rent and then we we need to
买房和租房的资料。然后，我们需要
know can we afford it is this part of
知道我们是否负担得起，这是否符合
our Rich Life vision what if one of us
我们“富裕生活”的愿景，如果我们其中一人不幸去世怎么办？
loses our job and on on on but then
我们的工作等等，但
second we need to say what kind of
其次，我们需要说说
Lifestyle do we want if we love to
我们想要什么样的生活方式。如果我们喜欢
decorate that's probably worth something
装饰，这可能很有价值，
we should maybe we need to buy a house
我们或许应该买房。
if we want our kids to be in a
如果我们想让孩子住在某个
particular area maybe we need to buy
特定区域，我们或许也需要买房。
buy or to rent and so we can't just do
买房或租房有很多非经济因素，所以我们不能只做其中之一。
one or the other but my main argument is
但我的主要观点是，
this most of us never run the numbers we
我们大多数人从来不计算成本。我们
will spend a million dollars in toal
会花一百万美元买房，
won't run one calculation so we got to
却不做任何计算。所以我们必须
play multiple notes doing the financial
多方考虑，兼顾经济
and non-financial parts I think that's
和非经济因素。我认为很多
what a lot of people are actually saying
人实际上都在说这一点。
a lot of people are saying you know I
很多人都在说，你知道，我
bought a house and this person is saying
买了房子，这个人说，
I used to be I used to live in a caravan
我以前住在房车里，现在
I finally bought a house and I don't
终于买了房子，我并不一定
care about being rich necessarily but
在意是否富有，但
having my own house means the world to
拥有自己的房子对
me great great non-financial reason they
我来说意义重大。他们想要稳定，这是一个非常重要的非经济原因，
want stability I totally value that I
我完全理解。我
would all also ask did you run the
也会问大家，你们计算过
numbers I think the key thing is most
成本吗？我认为关键在于，大多数
people when they buy the house they see
人在买房时，他们看到的是…… 他们认为这是
it as an investment and they see it as a
一种投资，而且他们认为这是一项
good investment I think in part because
不错的投资。我想部分原因是
they don't really know any other way to
他们真的不知道还有其他什么
invest totally right so we we grow up we
投资方式。没错，所以我们长大后会
think okay the minute you get enough
想，好吧，一旦你赚够了
money the first thing you have to do is
钱，第一件事就是
buy a house I mean there's a real
买房。我的意思是，
sequence of of events in our lives that
我们的人生中确实有一系列既定的事件：
are given to us which is go to school go
上学、
to college or university or something
上大学或
like that there get the degree get the
类似的课程、获得学位、找到
job buy the house get married have the
工作、买房、结婚、生
kids and then move to Florida get skin
孩子，然后搬到佛罗里达，得皮肤
cancer die oh retire okay have your
癌，去世，哦，退休，养老金也用完了。
pension die we don't have pensions
我们现在没有养老金了，
anymore that was in the 60s but yes and
那是60年代的事了。但是，
actually that's a pretty good life if
如果你仔细想想，这其实是一种相当不错的
good life especially the way that our
生活，尤其是对于我们
parents generation grew up where you
父母那一代人来说，
know they could buy a house on a
他们可以用
reasonable salary one salary but that
一份合理的工资买房。但
doesn't exist right now housing is
现在这种情况已经不存在了，房价一直
historically expensive um and not
居高不下。
through any fault of young people by the
顺便说一句，这并非年轻人的错。
thrown around the media young people are
媒体上有很多关于年轻人
buying too much avocado toast they're
买太多牛油果吐司、
always buying the new iPhone that's not
总是买新款iPhone之类的说法。
why housing is expensive housing is
房价高的原因并非如此，而是
expensive because people who bought
因为那些
their houses in the 60s 70s and 80s
在六七十年代和八十年代买房的人，他们
bought a house and then systematically
买了房子之后，就系统性地
prevented everyone else from building
阻止其他人建造
more housing so it is it's called
更多住房。这就是所谓的“邻避主义”（
nimbyism not in my backyard they have
NIMBY，即“不要建在我家后院”）。他们
allowed almost no housing to be built
几乎不允许建造任何住房，
particularly in the US that's why if you
尤其是在美国。这就是为什么如果
only have a limit Li mited Supply guess
供应有限，
what happens to the price it goes way up
价格会发生什么？它会飙升。这种情况正在
that's changing slowly housing prices
缓慢改变，
will in certain cities like Austin even
一些城市的房价，比如奥斯汀，甚至
Santa Monica have come down in certain
圣莫尼卡，在某些地区已经有所下降。
to build more housing so that young
建造更多住房非常重要，这样
people middleclass people poor people
年轻人、中产阶级和穷人
can afford housing we should not have
才能买得起房。我们不应该让
people unable to afford rent or buying
人们买不起房或租不起
housing it's a big problem so are you
房，这是一个大问题。所以你的意思是，
saying that the average couple if
如果一对普通夫妇
they're looking to make a financial
想
return yeah on their joint savings count
在他们的共同储蓄
account they shouldn't invest that money
账户中获得经济回报，他们不应该把钱投资
in a house I personally would not
到房子上？我个人不
consider my primary residents to be a
认为自住房屋是一项
great investment because it has massive
好的投资，因为它有巨大的
costs right massive um maintenance
成本，对吧？巨大的维护成本，首付的
opportunity cost of that down payment
机会成本。
let's say you put down 50k or 100K that
假设你支付了5万或10万美元的首付，那可能会……
could have been invested it has all
投资之后，
kinds of uh Phantom costs and then you
你会发现各种各样的隐形成本，然后你
have to stay there for until you pay it
还得一直住在那里直到还清贷款，
off presumably 30 years most people
大概需要30年。大多数人
don't stay for 30 years there's some
不会住满30年。抵押
shocking math behind a mortgage like
贷款背后有一些令人震惊的数学计算，比如
most people don't realize that they will
大多数人没有意识到，在最初的21年里，他们
be paying more towards their uh interest
支付的利息会比本金还多。
me say that again most people when they
我再说一遍，现在利率这么高，大多数人如果
take a 30-year mortgage right now with
选择30年期抵押贷款，那么
than they are towards the mortgage in
在第
year 1 2 5 10 year 20 until till finally
1年、第2年、第5年、第10年、第20年，他们支付的利息都会比本金还多，直到第
year 21 when they are finally paying
21年，他们才开始支付
more towards their mortgage their
更多的
principal rather than interest so you
本金而不是利息。所以，你
know that phrase I don't want to throw
知道那句“我不想把
money away on rent we might more aptly
钱浪费在房租上”，我们或许更应该
say I don't want to throw money away on
说“我不想把钱浪费在
interest so if I'm in a couple I'm in a
利息上”。假设
relationship and me and my partner have
我和我的伴侣有一段感情，我们攒了
managed to save I don't know 50k what is
5万英镑，那么如何
a better use of that 50k to drive a
更好地利用这5万英镑来获得更好的
financial
投资
return okay so let's simplify the whole
回报呢？好，我们来讨论一下。 简化一下，
thing I have a conscious spending plan I
我有一个理性消费计划，里面
have four numbers that couple should be
有四个数字，夫妻应该
talking about okay the first off is your
好好谈谈。首先是
fixed costs those should be roughly 50
固定支出，这部分支出应该占到
to 60% of your take-home pay and what's
税后收入的50%到60%。什么是固定支出呢？
the fixed cost fixed cost includes your
固定支出包括
housing or uh that could be rent
住房，比如房租、房贷、水电煤气费、
mortgage your utilities your car payment
车贷、
any debt payment anything that is
任何债务，以及任何固定支出，
consistent even groceries that you need
甚至包括你
to live every single month so 50% of my
每个月生活必需的食品杂货。所以，我每月收入的50%
monthly income go straight to those
直接用于这些
fixed costs monthly take-home post tax
固定支出。税后到手收入，也就是税后收入。50%
post tax okay 50 to 60% is the number
到60%就是
you want to be targeting right there is
你应该努力达到的目标。这
um is the Crux of why couples are
就是夫妻们
stressed out about money it's because
为钱发愁的症结所在：
they are spending too much on fixed
他们在固定
costs and within that there's two areas
支出上花得太多了。其中有两个方面
they spend too much on you know what
他们花得太多。
they are housing is number one because
第一是住房，因为房价
it's so expensive and they don't
太贵，他们又不
calculate number two is cars usually
计算。第二是汽车，通常是
trucks we love trucks trucks and SUVs in
卡车。在美国，我们喜欢卡车和SUV。
America the cultural script is oh we're
文化观念是：哦，我们要有
having a kid we need to get a big house
孩子了，我们需要买个大房子
and a big SUV uh because we do so that
和一辆大SUV，因为我们确实需要。 所以，这就是
right there is where people get stressed
人们在金钱方面感到压力的地方。
money next number is your savings this
接下来是储蓄，
should be 5 to 10% minimum this includes
至少应该占收入的5%到10%。这
your emergency fund this includes saving
包括你的应急基金、
for a down payment anything you're
首付储蓄，以及任何你未来
between 1 to five years basically okay
1到5年内不需要的钱。好的，
next up is Investments this would be 5
接下来是投资，至少也应该占收入的5%
to 10% minimum this is where real wealth
到10%。这才是真正创造财富的地方，也是
is created and this is where couples
夫妻们常常
neglect they they talk about saving and
忽略的地方。他们谈论储蓄，会
they'll say oh we try to save I don't
说：“哦，我们努力存钱，但我不会
try to brush my teeth I don't try to
刻意去刷牙，我不会刻意去
save I make it automatic that's what I
存钱，我会让它成为一种习惯。” 这正是我
want couples to do that's what I cover
希望夫妻们做到的，也是我
in the book and then finally my favorite
在书中讲解的内容。最后，我最喜欢的
category of all guilt-free spending this
类别是无愧于心的消费，比如
is going out for drinks concerts travel
外出喝酒、看演唱会、旅行。
20 to 35% of take-home pay that's a lot
拿出税后收入的20%到35%来花掉，这可是
that's a lot if you look at it people go
一大笔钱，如果你仔细想想，人们都会
wow yes and when you get down to that
惊叹。是的，当你把钱花在这个
number and you're out and you're having
比例上，
drinks with your friends or you're out
和朋友们出去喝酒，或者享受
to a beautiful experience you don't have
美好的体验时，你就不必
to worry about anything else you don't
担心其他任何事情了。 你
have to feel guilty or anxious because
不必感到内疚或焦虑，因为
you're already handling all these other
你已经处理好了其他
three numbers you know you're set and
三个数字，你知道你已经准备好了，
you have this money set aside and you
你已经存下了这笔钱，你
can enjoy it guilt free so this 10 this
可以毫无愧疚地享受它。所以，这
sort of 10% that is automatically
10%的自动
invested would you set up some kind of
投资，你会设置某种
system that automatically invests it
自动投资系统吗？
always always you should not be doing
永远不要
any of this manually so your investment
手动操作，你的投资
should be happening automatically and
应该自动进行。
for a couple you actually get to
对于情侣来说，你们实际上可以
celebrate it every month you have a
每个月庆祝一下，你们可以
monthly money meeting where you talk
每月举行一次“财务会议”，讨论
about money every month most couples
财务状况。大多数情侣
don't do this you will now after
都不会这样做，
watching this and you talk about it you
看完这个视频后，你们会明白的。你们会讨论
look at how your Investments are doing
你们的投资情况，互相
you give each other a high five a big
击掌、
hug congratulations and once you do this
拥抱、祝贺。一旦你们
for six months a year you really start
每年坚持六个月，你们就会真正开始
to see how it adds up fast what if your
看到积蓄增长的速度。如果你的
partner wants to buy a house and you
伴侣想买房而你
don't o that's tricky how would you
不想怎么办？这很棘手，你会如何
handle it um it depends on my level of
处理？嗯，这取决于我对这个
conviction about the decision I think
决定的信念程度。我认为
you got to pick your battles and
你必须有所取舍，有所坚持。
relationships but um I am probably more
但我可能
aware than my partner because my brother
比我的伴侣更有理财意识，因为我的兄弟就是这样。 他是
is he's been an investment banker for 13
一位投资银行家，从业13
years he works for me full-time he's my
年了，他全职为我工作​​，是我的
money guy yeah okay he's my older
理财顾问。是的，好吧，他是我
brother where does he charge you 1.5% uh
哥哥。他收你1.5%的佣金吗？呃，
he doesn't charge me a percentage on my
他不收我任何佣金，所以我很
P so happy no he works full-time in the
满意。不，他在公司全职工作，
business so he
所以
he manages much of my money but he would
他管理着我的大部分资金。但他会跟
make the case to me of pretty much the
我解释的，基本上跟
case you've made yeah so based on an
你说的差不多。是的，基于
opportunity cost basis I a lot of people
机会成本，很多人
don't even know what opportunity cost is
甚至不知道机会成本是什么，
I'm going to Hazard a guess I'm going
我来大胆猜测一下，我
try and explain it which is essentially
试着解释一下，它本质上就是
all the things you could have done with
你可以用这笔钱做的所有事情。是的，
this money instead yes so based on all
基于你所有
the opportunities you have available to
可用的机会，
you Steve is buying this house a good
史蒂夫，买这套房子是合理
use of that money and the answer was
利用这笔钱吗？答案
actually no when I bought my first house
实际上是否定的。当我第一次买房时，答案是
it was no unless this is a emotional
否定的，除非这是一个情感上的
decision
决定，
because you and your partner want a
比如你和你的伴侣想要一种
psychological feeling of safety to bring
心理上的安全感来
up the kids whatever it might be just a
抚养孩子，或者其他什么原因。
then if it is Steve if that's why you
如果是这样，史蒂夫，如果这就是你
want to buy it and you think you're
想买房的原因，而且你认为你会在
going to stay there for a considerable
那里住相当长一段时间，
amount of years then go ahead we're
那就买吧。 我们
going to kind of section this as a
要把这件事单独拿出来，和
your Investments what you do I did
你的其他投资理由有所不同。你做了什么？我
exactly what he said you bought it
完全按照他说的做了，
knowing it was an emotional decision
明知这是个情绪化的决定，
yeah I bought it knowing it was a bad
还是买了。是的，我明知这是个糟糕的决定，还是买了。
decision I love this yeah okay this is
我喜欢这个。好的，这
amazing everybody listen closely cuz I
太棒了，大家仔细听，因为我
want to break down what you just said in
想用另一种方式来解释你刚才说的。
in a different term first off you got to
首先，你得
run the numbers yeah always for the
算算账。是的，对于
biggest purchases in your life you need
人生中最大的一笔消费，你总是需要
to calculate carefully what's my buy
仔细计算：买
versus rent what's my opportunity cost
和租哪个更划算？我的机会成本是多少？它的
what's it going to amortise at all these
摊销期是多久？所有这些
things that most people are not familiar
大多数人都不熟悉的东西，去
with learn it it's not that complicated
学学吧，其实没那么复杂。
second you need to factor in the
其次，你需要考虑
non-financial hey why am I doing this do
非财务因素。嘿，我为什么要这么做？
I just feel this certain way there's
我只是有这种感觉吗？
about money nothing you want to buy this
对金钱感到非理性并没有错，你想买这件
thing and it's a bad financial decision
东西，但这在财务上是个糟糕的决定。
okay first can I afford it if so we can
好的，首先，我能买得起吗？如果能，我们可以
continue the conversation and then you
继续讨论。然后你
buy it Eyes Wide Open saying I know it's
睁大眼睛买了它，说：我知道这
not an investment I know it's not even a
不是投资，我知道这甚至不是一个
good Financial DEC fact it's a terrible
好的财务决定，事实上，这是一个糟糕的
financial and I'm still going to do it
财务决定。 我还是会这么做。
when I when my wife and I go to buy a
等我和妻子将来买房的时候，
decision of Our Lives we already know
我知道这会是我们人生中最糟糕的财务决定，
that but we will probably still do it
但我们可能还是会这么做，就像
anyway same as you because there's more
你一样。因为
to life than just what's in a
生活远不止电子
spreadsheet but you have to know know
表格里的内容。但在
make these big decisions and you have to
做这些重大决定之前，你必须了解所有因素，而且你必须和
be able to do it with your partner you
你的伴侣一起做决定。你
know it'd be very easy for you to do
知道，你
things unilaterally it'd be very easy
单方面做决定很容易，
for me to do it as well what I've
我单方面做决定也很容易。我
learned and what I emphasize on my
学到的，也是我
podcast every episode is just because
每期播客都在强调的，即使
you may be the higher earner or have
你收入更高或
more money it's actually your obligation
更有钱，你也有义务
to bring your partner in and to get them
让你的伴侣参与进来。
involved and they may not be as Savvy or
他们可能不像你那么精通，甚至可能没那么
even as interested but you have to find
感兴趣，但你必须找到
a way to bring them into this world and
一种方法让他们了解这个世界，让他们
get them connected with you with my wife
和你建立联系。当然，我和我妻子更懂投资，
Investments so I'm doing our investments
所以我负责我们的投资，
but we're still talking about them we're
但我们仍然会讨论这些投资，我们会
saying like hey here's the numbers we
说：“嘿，这是我们
chose are we still good with that let's
选择的数字，我们觉得合适吗？” 咱们来
take a look at it high five you know
看看，击掌！你知道，
here's what we're thinking for next year
这就是我们对明年的想法，这就是
that's the level we're talking about
我们讨论的水平。
these are these are exactly the kind of
这些正是
conversations you want to have and I I'm
你想要进行的对话。我很
actually really thrilled you shared that
高兴你分享了这个
example because I celebrate that you
例子，因为我为你
made a bad financial investment because
做了一笔糟糕的投资而感到高兴，因为
it wasn't an investment it was just
那根本不是投资，只是
something you wanted and you could
你想要的东西，而且你也买得起。是的，
it yeah and we're both aware me and my
我和我的
partner we had the conversation we're
伴侣都意识到了这一点，我们讨论过，我们都
both aware that um this is one of the
意识到，
money on if our objective if our kpi our
如果我们的目标，或者说我们的
key performance indicator was to make
关键绩效指标（KPI）是赚
more money this was a terrible decision
更多钱，那么这是我们能把钱花在的最糟糕的事情之一。这是一个糟糕的决定。是的，
to make yes but we're also aware we just
但我们也意识到，我们只是
didn't care we thought you know it's
不在乎，我们觉得，你知道，
this decision and I think that's what
这个决定有很多非金钱方面的好处，我认为这才是
most people don't realize actually and I
大多数人没有意识到的。我
just think about my friends I think most
想想我的朋友们，我认为他们中的大多数人
of my friends believe that when they buy
认为，他们
their house they're doing so because
买房是因为
they don't know they don't know any
他们不知道，他们不知道还有
other way to invest Society hasn't given
其他投资社会的方式。 并没有给
us an alternative so what is the
我们提供替代方案，那么替代方案是什么呢？
alternative simple lowcost long-term
简单、低成本的长期
index funds are fantastic ways to invest
指数基​​金是绝佳的投资方式。
I'll explain what they are the myth
我会解释一下它们是什么。
about investing is that you have to sit
关于投资的一个误区是，你必须坐在
there and look at PE ratios and things
那里研究市盈率之类的东西。
like that no you pick often one One Fund
不，你通常只需要选择一只基金。
there's a simple example called a Target
有一个简单的例子叫做目标
date fund you pick the year you're going
日期基金，你选择你
to retire in like if I'm going to retire
退休的年份，比如如果我打算
in 2050 I pick a Vanguard 2050 fund or
在2050年退休，我会选择Vanguard 2050基金、
Fidelity or Schwab 2050 fund all I do is
Fidelity 2050基金或Schwab 2050基金。我所做的就是
literally send money every single month
每个月都往基金里投钱，
I set it up so it happens automatically
我设置了自动投币，
it could be $50 a month 500 500,000 per
可以是每月50美元、500美元，甚至是
month and that's all I do I just send it
每月50万美元。这就是我所做的，我只需要把钱投
there it automatically buys the stock
进去，它就会自动购买股票，
market it automatically diversifies and
自动分散投资，并且
gets more conservative over time and
随着时间的推移变得更加保守。就是这样。
that's it so you know the Fitness World
你知道，在健身领域，
you've I've seen you training you you've
我看到你训练，你
learned about Fitness when you first
学习健身，当你刚
start off so much information and so
开始的时候，你会收到很多信息，
many different people giving you
很多人会给你
different pieces of advice right it's
不同的建议，对吧？
like oh my God how am I supposed to know
我的天啊，我怎么可能知道
what about my genetics and this and that
我的基因等等这些？
and then over time you realize oh it's
然后随着时间的推移，你会意识到，哦，其实
actually pretty simple once you cut
很简单，一旦你拨开
through the noise that's the same thing
迷雾，一切都会变得清晰明了。
with money that's the same thing with
金钱和
investing you have to cut through the
投资也是如此，你必须拨开
noise and it actually becomes
迷雾，它就会变得
shockingly simple oh my God this is the
出奇地简单。我的天啊，这才是
way that real wealth is created it's
真正财富的创造方式：
about consistent investing it's about
持续投资，把握
time it's about low fees that's it and
时机，低费用，就是这样。
you start to wonder what's all this
你会开始疑惑，
these magazines and newspapers and on
杂志、报纸和
Tik Tok it's just noise do you know when
TikTok上那些铺天盖地的东西到底是什么？它们只是噪音。你知道吗，当
you sat down with those 180 odd couples
你和大约180对情侣坐下来
you've spoken to about money in their in
谈论他们
their relationship have you not had
关系中的金钱问题时，你有没有遇到过
moments where one of the partners was
其中一方感到
shocked always for better in F us yeah
震惊的时刻？总是朝着好的方向发展。是的，
yeah actually yes um sometimes they are
确实如此。有时候，他们在
shocked before they meet me because I
见我之前就会感到震惊，因为我
have them prepare their document with
会让他们准备好
their financials and one of them has
财务文件，而他们中的一方，有时甚至是
financials sometimes both and they
双方，从未真正看过自己的财务状况。他们
realize it's much worse than they
意识到情况比他们想象的要糟糕得多，
thought or it's much better sometimes
或者比他们想象的要好得多。
we're talking and a one of the partners
我们正在交谈，其中一位伴侣
will actually talk about how they feel
会第一次敞开心扉地谈论自己的感受，
for the first time ever and the other
而另一位
partner will be crying give me some
伴侣则会哭泣。请举例说明
examples of the moments that you
你
remember that shocked you the
记忆中最让你震惊的时刻。
most I think
我想到的最令人
about one of the most shocking examples
震惊的例子之一
was a woman who was around the age of
是一位
mid-40s maybe 50 and she had had a
大约40岁到50岁的女士，她做了
double lung
双肺
transplant and um she had successfully
移植手术，手术很成功，她还
had the transplant and she was alive um
活着，身体也很
she was healthy but she knew that she
健康，但她知道
what the doctors told her and she said I
医生告诉她，她还能再活5到10年。她说：“我
want to share this time with my
想和我的女儿们一起度过这段时光，
daughters they were around 11 and 12 her
她们当时大约11岁和12岁。”她的
husband and um I want to do that I said
丈夫也说：“我想这样做。”我说：“
okay what's stopping you and she said um
好的，是什么阻止了你？”她说：“嗯，
well I still have a job and I looked at
我还有工作。”我查看了
her financials they were
她的财务状况，他们是
multi-millionaires they had saved
千万富翁，他们长期坚持
consistently doing index funds over time
投资指数基金，
nothing fancy just consistent investing
没有任何花哨的技巧，只是持续投资。
they she could stop working tomorrow and
她明天就可以停止工作，
they would have enough
他们也有足够的
money
钱
forever she couldn't stop she said I
一辈子。但她不能停止工作，她说：“我
like to work I like knowing that I have
喜欢工作，我喜欢知道自己有
a job I like the consistent income so
工作，我喜欢稳定的收入。”所以
most people are used to getting an
大多数人都习惯了……
income and that's why they find it so
收入是他们难以企及的，这也是他们
difficult to retire among other reasons
难以退休的原因之一，
because the income will stop even though
因为收入一旦停止就会消失。即使
I can point out to them the Investment
我可以向他们指出
Portfolio you've built and Social
你建立的投资组合、
Security and all these things will
社保以及所有这些福利
actually pay you people are terrified of
实际上都会给你带来收入，人们仍然害怕
not seeing that money come into their
看不到钱进入他们的
checking account in this case she had a
支票账户。在这个例子中，她有一个…… 就像
ticking clock we all have a clock but
我们每个人都有时间一样，但
she knew how long hers would go for she
她知道自己的时间还能走多久。她
found it incredibly difficult to quit
发现
her job and spend time with her
辞职去陪伴
daughters now if we're listening to this
女儿们无比艰难。如果我们正在听这个故事，我们会觉得“
it's like just quit it's so obvious to
辞职吧”，这道理显而易见，
us but we're not the ones making the
但我们却不是做
decision that was quite shocking to hear
决定的人。听到她即使
how difficult it can be even in cases of
在生死攸关的情况下，想要一份稳定的收入也会如此艰难，这着实令人震惊。那么，
what role does earning play like just
收入又扮演着怎样的角色呢？仅仅是
earning more money playing all of this
赚更多的钱，诸如此类的事情，
stuff because I think I did I'm gonna be
因为我觉得我以前也这样。说实话，
honest I had a bias when I was 18 19
我18、19岁的时候确实有偏见。那时候
years old um I was fairly Reckless with
我
money and I had these four credit cards
花钱大手大脚，有四张信用卡，
I maxed out the credit cards I blew the
刷爆了，把
money I got two ccjs which is a county
钱都挥霍掉了，还收到了两份CCJ（
court judgment in the UK okay had huge
英国的郡法院判决）。好吧，我背负着
debts of thousands of thousands of
数万
pounds and and in my head I thought it
英镑的巨额债务。我当时的想法是，
will be fine if I just earn more no
只要我赚更多的钱就行了，
because I'm G to earn so much money that
因为我有能力赚很多钱，就能
I'll just outpace this problem and that
摆脱困境。这就是
was like my bias my bias was like I'll
我的偏见，我的偏见。 我当时的想法是，只要努力
just earn loads of money and when I
赚钱就行了。后来我
figured out what a credit score was and
弄明白了信用评分是什么，发现
that mine was destroyed I thought that
我的信用评分已经崩塌了，但我心想这也没关系，
won't matter because I'll always pay in
反正我以后都用
cash yeah classic um every couple I
现金支付。真是老一套。我跟所有
speak to who has a spending problem they
有消费问题的夫妇聊过，他们
always say the same thing they go we
总是说同样的话：我们
just need to earn more and these are the
只需要多挣点钱。但当
very same couples when we crunch their
我们帮他们
numbers they'll often realize they were
算账的时候，他们往往会意识到自己
earning way more than they thought and
赚的钱比想象中多得多。
you can see their faces cuz I have the
你可以看看他们的表情，因为我把
whole thing on YouTube and it's this
整个过程都上传到YouTube了。他们意识到这一点的时候，会
realization that oh my God the story
惊呼：“天哪，
I've been telling myself if we just earn
我之前一直安慰自己，如果我们能多挣
$25,000 more and then they realize we
2.5万美元就好了！”然后他们意识到自己
actually are earning 25k more and they
真的多挣了2.5万美元，却不
don't know what to do with it what I
知道该怎么花。我会
tell them is you could be making
告诉他们，就算你
$300,000 more right now and it would not
现在多挣30万美元，也根本没用，
make one bit of difference because
因为
you're you have a hole in your bucket
你的钱都花光了，根本没用。
the next thing I ask over Spenders is um
接下来我会问这些花钱大手大脚的人，
do you want to make no change small
你们是想保持现状、小幅
change or big changes 100% of them say
调整还是大幅改变？答案是100%。 当他们说要做出
big changes I go all right I take them
重大改变时，我会说好吧，我相信他们的
at their word and then we start going
话，然后我们开始逐项
down the list and they find it
讨论。他们发现，
incredibly difficult to strip out even
即使是削减
the most minor of spending so we have a
最微小的开支也难如登天。比如，有一对
couple here that will be in literally
夫妇
hundreds of thousands of dollars of debt
负债数十万美元，
watching them and they're very calm it's
看着他们这样，我简直要心脏病发作了，但他们却非常冷静。这是
because I understand interest rates and
因为我了解利率，也
I know what situation they're in and so
知道他们目前的处境。所以，
they go big changes suddenly 10 minutes
他们一开始说要做出重大改变，但10分钟
later we're debating whether they can
后，我们却在讨论他们是否还能
keep their Netflix subscription or not
继续订阅Netflix。
and I go guys I'm not here to berate you
我会说：“伙计们，我不是来责骂你们的，
I'm not the teacher who's telling the
我不是老师，不会对孩子说‘
kid you've been a bad kid which deep
你做错了’。其实，很多人，包括我们
down a lot of them want a lot of us want
很多人，内心深处都渴望
an authority figure to tell you you've
权威人士告诉我们‘你做错了，
been bad now we got to be good and
现在你必须变好’，但我
that's just not what I do I help them
不会这样做。我会帮助他们
realize it themselves and it goes slower
自己意识到这一点。这个过程比较慢，
it takes a long time but if they realize
需要很长时间，但如果他们
it themselves they're able to make the
自己意识到了，他们就能做出
change every couple says they want to
改变。每对夫妇都说他们想要
make big changes when it gets down to
做出重大改变，但真正涉及到
the spending is really difficult that's
开支时，却发现这真的很难。这就是
why you have to be incredibly careful
为什么我们需要……” 你必须非常谨慎地选择
which lifestyle purchases you make that
那些与
are tied to your identity so if you are
你的身份认同紧密相关的消费品。比如，如果你是
a car person and you're driving a
个爱车之人，开着一辆
Rolls-Royce really fancy car it will be
劳斯莱斯之类的豪车，那么
incredibly difficult for you to
你很难接受
downgrade that car because it's part of
换辆便宜的车，因为它已经成为
your identity right meanwhile like if
你身份的一部分。而如果
you have to get cheaper paper towels
你需要买便宜的纸巾之类的东西，
whatever nobody cares but you have to be
没人会在意。但你必须
very careful about what you allow to
非常小心地选择哪些东西会
become part of your identity I'm not
成为你身份认同的一部分。我不是
saying don't buy nice things and couples
说不要买好东西，情侣们
you should buy nice things but do it
应该买，但要确保自己
when you know that you can afford to do
能够
it forever don't just do it because oh
长期负担得起。不要因为“
we want to buy private school this year
我们今年想送孩子上私立学校，
but we don't know how to pay for it next
但不知道明年怎么付钱”就盲目消费。
year so do you think that couple should
你觉得这对情侣应该
make a
制定预算吗？
budget uh I don't like budgets I don't
嗯，我不喜欢预算，我觉得预算没用，它总是
think they work I think they look
着眼于过去，而有
backwards whereas a conscious spending
意识的消费
plan looks forward but most couples
计划则着眼于未来。但大多数情侣内心
think deep down we just need to create a
深处都觉得我们需要制定一个
budget isn't a budget the thing you gave
预算。你之前跟
me like the 50% 60% different a budget
我说的预算和现在的预算有50%到60%的区别，预算
is couples tracking every last line item
是指情侣们追踪每一笔支出，
they're tracking how much they spent on
追踪他们如何…… 他们记录了自己花了多少钱买
corn they're tracking how much they
玉米，也记录了自己花了多少
spent on diapers someone has to create
钱买尿布。总得有人创建
and track this laborious spreadsheet and
并记录这份繁琐的电子表格，
then at the end of the month they look
然后在月底，他们
at it and they go
看看，然后说：“
uh I guess we spent that much what are
嗯，我猜我们花了这么多钱，那这些钱该怎么花呢？”
you supposed to do with that most
大多数
couples have no idea does this budget
夫妻都不知道。这份预算能
tell you when you're going to be a
告诉你什么时候能成为
millionaire does it tell you what your
百万富翁吗？能告诉你你的
net worth is does it tell you if you
净资产是多少吗？能告诉你你的钱
enough no it doesn't stack up to
够不够吗？不，它
anything it's just a bunch of numbers
什么都说明不了，它只是一堆记录
tracking budgets Look Backwards a
预算的数字而已。回顾过去，有
conscious spending plan looks forward so
意识的消费计划着眼未来。有
a conscious spending plan allows you to
意识的消费计划能让你
zoom out and say what is the vision for
跳出固有思维，思考
our RIS rich life how do we pick the
我们理想中的富裕生活是什么样的。我们如何选择
things we want to spend extravagantly on
想要挥霍的项目，
and cut cost mercilessly on the things
并在不需要的项目上毫不留情地削减开支？
we don't so I give you these numbers 50
所以我给出这些数字：
to 60% for fixed costs it's up to you
固定支出占50%到60%。至于如何
how you want to hit the number if you
达到这个目标，就看你自己了。如果你
love your house you want to spend more
爱你的房子，你想
on your house do it maybe it means you
在房子上多花钱，那就去做吧。也许这意味着你要
spend less on your car payment if you
减少汽车贷款的支出。如果你
want to um go to concerts but you don't
想去看演唱会，那就…… 你
care about eating out fantastic take the
不在乎下馆子，太棒了，去
trip go see Taylor Swift so it's up to
旅行吧，去看泰勒·斯威夫特的演唱会，所以如何
you to make the tetris pieces fit but
把俄罗斯方块拼起来就看你自己了，
you decide and all your money flows for
你的决定，你的所有钱都流向了
those four
那四个
numbers how do we go about teaching our
数字。我们该如何教
kids about money my my older brother and
孩子理财呢？我的哥哥，也就是
the one that works in our company he has
我们公司的一个同事，有
three kids under the age of six and I'm
三个六岁以下的孩子。我很
wondering because he's such an Optimizer
好奇，因为他是个精打细算的人，我的孩子以后会不会也变成
optimizers is there a relationship
精打细算的人？
between our parents and our kids and if
父母和孩子之间应该有什么关系？如果
I want to when I do have my kids how do
我以后有了孩子，
I make sure that they aren't worriors or
我该如何确保他们不会成为焦虑的人，或者
avoid is the number one thing that the
逃避理财？那些
couples in financial trouble say is when
陷入财务困境的夫妇最常提到的一点是，
they were growing up their parents never
他们小时候父母从来
talked about money never there was an
不谈钱。
episode on our podcast with this uh
我们播客有一期节目，讲的是一对
couple living in Kansas in a low cost of
住在堪萨斯州低
living area and um they were making
消费地区的夫妇，他们
$130,000 a year that's a very good
年收入13万美元，这在
income especially for their area they
他们那个地区算是非常不错的收入了，他们
should have had tons of money tons of
应该有很多钱，很多
savings but their daughter came home one
积蓄。但是有一天，他们的女儿
day with um food from the school because
从学校带回了食物，因为
she had told her school we don't have
她告诉学校他们没钱了。
have enough money to eat now they had
现在他们有足够的钱吃饭了，因为他们家以前有
plenty of money why because her mom and
很多钱。为什么呢？因为她的
dad were always saying we don't have
父母总是说我们钱不够，
enough we can't afford it daughter took
我们买不起。女儿把
that message to school and was given
这种想法带到了学校，结果学校给了她
free food this was horrifying to the dad
免费的食物。这让爸爸感到非常震惊，非常震惊。
horrifying and what he realized at that
他那
moment was the way that I'm
一刻意识到，我跟孩子
communicating about money is not
谈论金钱的方式
working see most parents deep down
行不通。大多数父母内心深处都
believe that money is something to
认为金钱是应该
protect kids from they think it's bad
保护孩子免受其害的东西，他们认为金钱是坏的。
deep down most Americans we we have a
大多数美国人对
LoveHate relationship with money but
金钱都有一种爱恨交织的复杂情感。但
parents think their kids let them be
父母认为应该让孩子享受
kids but you would never teach a kid how
童年。但你永远不会教孩子
to ride a bike by saying we don't talk
骑自行车时说“我们家不谈
about bikes in this
自行车”，
family you would get them a bike you
你会给他们一辆自行车，让他们骑上去，
would get them on you would show them
教他们
how to do it you would let them fall and
怎么骑，让他们摔倒，
then you would help them get up again so
然后再扶他们起来。
imagine this with your kids imagine that
想象一下你的孩子，想象一下
they are three years old young you pull
他们三岁，你把
them up sit them you say look can you
他们扶起来坐好，说：“看，你能帮
help me push this button we're gonna pay
我按一下这个按钮吗？我们要付
for the rent this is for our beautiful
房租了，这是我们漂亮
house help me push that button yay give
房子的租金，帮我按一下这个按钮。”耶！和他们击掌！
them five okay getting them involved
好，从一开始就让他们参与进来。
they're living with two parents this is
他们和父母住在一起，这是
Mom and Dad you want them to see both
爸爸妈妈。你想让他们看到父母双方，
because too often people only see um Mom
因为人们常常只看到妈妈
worrying about the bills and so they
为账单操心，所以他们
come to associate mom with worrying and
会把妈妈和操心联系起来，
therefore if it's their daughter they
因此如果是女儿，他们也会
think they are supposed to worry as well
觉得女儿也应该操心。
now imagine the kid is uh 8 10 years old
想象一下，孩子八九岁，
you say hey we have to go to the grocery
你说：“嘿，我们得去
store here's $100 we need to get all
超市，这里有100美元，我们需要买
these things how should we do it let
这些东西，我们该怎么做？”
them let them make mistakes they're
让他们犯错，让他们自己去学，他们会
going to forget about taxes let them
忘记税收，让他们从中
learn right they get a little older
学习。等他们长大一些，
they're planning uh pizza or a
他们开始计划吃披萨还是去
restaurant for the family here's $100
餐厅，这里有100美元
for dinner problem is they're going to
晚餐钱。问题是，他们可能会
pick some place like Chili's it's
选像Chili's这样的地方，虽然很
horrible but you got to go let them
糟糕，但你得让他们去，让他们从中
learn their lesson by the time they are
吸取教训。等到他们
16 years old they have planned a family
16岁的时候，他们已经计划过家庭
vacation they are aware of tradeoffs
旅行，他们了解权衡取舍、税收、小费等等，
taxes tips all kinds of stuff they have
他们还
helped the family buy its new car this
帮助家里买了新车。这
is how you prepare kids you don't simply
就是你培养孩子的方式。你不能简单地
say we don't talk about money in this
说“我们家不谈钱”，而是
family you let them learn about money
让他们自己去学习。 关于金钱，
and you tell them what you've learned
你要告诉他们你学到的
about money that's how you teach them
关于金钱的知识，这就是你教他们的方式。
I'm somewhat scared of my kids being
我有点担心我的孩子会变成
sport brats and I say to my partner
体育小霸王，我有时会跟我的伴侣说，如果
sometimes I'm like if when we have kids
我们有了孩子，是不是应该把
should we be putting the kids in like
他们放在……
the back of the l oh yeah you know what
你知道
I mean or should we should they be
我的意思吗？或者他们应该坦诚地告诉
upfront with us like what's the deal
我们到底是怎么回事？
well I'll tell you what I I um I went to
好吧，我告诉你，我
Public School uh my entire childhood and
整个童年都在公立学校度过，
then I got a bunch of scholarships and
后来我获得了一些奖学金，
went to a private school and for college
去了私立学校，上了大学。
and at that college I remember in the
在那所大学里，我记得
first week so many of the beliefs I had
第一周，我
about money and kids were shattered I
关于金钱和孩子的很多想法都被打破了。我
had always assumed that if you went to a
一直认为，如果你上了
private school you were spoiled and you
私立学校，你就会被宠坏，你
didn't really like to to work within 3
也不喜欢学习。三天之内，
days I realized that was totally untrue
我就意识到这完全是错误的。
like some kids are spoiled some are not
有些孩子被宠坏了，有些则不是。这
the correlation with private school not
和私立学校并没有太大关系，
really there it's about parents it's
这和父母有关，和
about how they were taught and it's also
他们如何被教育有关，也有
about some element of luck as well but
一些运气成分。但是
can you teach kids not to be spoiled yes
你能教孩子不被宠坏吗？是的，有很多方法可以做到。
there are so many wealthy kids who grew
很多富裕家庭的孩子
up not entitled appreciating what they
从小就没有被灌输的“知足常乐”观念，他们并不珍惜自己所
have and the parents were still like hey
拥有的一切，而父母却仍然会说：“嘿，
I want to go to a nice hotel how how do
我想去一家好酒店。” 那么，该如何
you raise kids that AR spoil what you
培养孩子，才能让他们拥有正确的理财观念呢？答案是：从孩子很小的时候就开始
beginning when you're teaching them
教他们，
about let's do this together money is
让他们明白金钱是
something that we all do together now
我们共同拥有的东西。
imagine that when you're talking to your
想象一下，当你和
family just the same way we talk about
家人谈论如何
creating a healthy relationship with
与
food right how do you teach your kids to
食物建立健康的联系时，就像我们谈论如何
have a healthy relationship with food
与食物建立健康的联系一样，该如何教孩子建立健康的金钱观呢？你们会经常谈论食物，
the grocery store together you cut
一起去超市，
carrots together and potatoes and you
一起切胡萝卜、土豆，然后
say this is why we're putting potatoes
解释为什么要把土豆放进
in this thing but we never do that with
这个菜里。但是，我们从来不会用这种方式来谈论
money so you have a healthy relationship
金钱。所以，要建立健康的金钱观，就要引导他们关注
with money by shining a light on it by
金钱，通过
talking and asking them questions do you
谈话和提问来引导他们。比如：“你
know how we afford this house um what's
知道我们是怎么买得起这栋房子的吗？”“使用
a good thing to do with credit cards and
信用卡应该怎么用，不应该怎么用？”“
cards hey what do you think that we have
嘿，我们手头有
200 bucks and we want to give it to a
200美元，想捐给一个
worthy cause how should we do it how
有意义的慈善机构，你觉得应该怎么做？
should we pick these are the kind of
应该选择哪个机构？”等等。
conversations that families should be
这是家庭应该
having and when kids start to engage
进行的对话。当孩子们开始接触
with money and they see parents doing it
金钱，看到父母如何理财，
and they realize it's not something to
意识到这不是什么丢脸
be ashamed of or hidden from they go oh
或需要隐瞒的事情时，他们会惊呼：“
my gosh like I have some agency over
天哪，我也能掌控金钱了！” 这就是
this some control that's how you prevent
防止他们被
them from being spoiled have you got
宠坏的方法。你有
kids yet no when you have kids if your
孩子了吗？还没有。等你有了孩子，如果你的
kids come to you and they say Dad um I
孩子来找你说：“爸爸，我
want to be rich mother love it I would
想变得有钱。” 妈妈，我喜欢这样。我会
say what does rich mean to you it means
问：“对你来说，富有意味着什么？” 答案是：
being able to have Financial Freedom so
财务自由。这意味着去
go into restaurants or shops or when I'm
餐厅、商店或者在
browsing Amazon I can just take care of
亚马逊上购物时不用看价格标签，我可以照顾好
myself I can live somewhere nice drive a
自己，可以住在舒适的地方，开
nice car go on a holiday when I want
好车，想去哪儿就去哪儿。这就是
it's freedom and what is the most
自由。那么，为了
thinking about to create that wealth and
创造和
preserve it so that I can be
保住财富，让自己变得
rich well you'll first noticed that when
富有，我应该考虑的最重要的事情是什么呢？你会注意到，当
this hypothetical kid said I want to be
这个假设的孩子说“我想变得
rich what was my response what you mean
有钱”时，我的反应是什么？“你说的‘富有’是什么意思？” 是啊，
by Rich yeah amazing what do you mean by
太棒了！“你说的‘富有’是什么意思？” （
Rich so excitement and curiosity the
兴奋和好奇）
opposite would be why do you want to be
相反的情况是：“你为什么想变得有钱？
rich you don't need to be rich that's
你不需要变得富有。” 富有
not for People Like Us squashing those
不是我们这种人的专利，扼杀他们的
dreams so when um like my nephew um a
梦想。比如，
few thanksgivings ago he was young and
几年前的感恩节，我的侄子还小，
he said um I want to buy a
他说：“我想买一块
Rolex amazing where'd you get that tell
劳力士，太棒了！你从哪儿弄来的？告诉
me what kind of Rolex how you going to
我你打算买哪款劳力士？你要怎么做？要多少钱？要攒
much do you have to save to put that
多少钱才能买得起？”
aside that's encouraging kids now they
鼓励孩子，他们
can figure out these trade-offs later
以后可以自己权衡利弊，
but just encouraging them first off is
但首先鼓励他们，是
the first thing we do with kids when
我们和孩子谈论金钱时做的第一件事。
they talk about money kids are smart
孩子们很聪明，
they notice by age three four or five
三四五岁的时候就能察觉到
how their parents feel about money I
父母对金钱的态度。我
talk to parents all the time and I speak
经常和父母交流，也和
to my own family and their parents of
我的家人以及他们
younger
年幼
kids they will tell me my four-year-old
孩子的父母交流。他们会告诉我，我四岁的女儿已经开始
is already worried about money every
担心钱了，
time she gets a little bit of money she
每次拿到一点零花钱，她都会把它
puts it in an envelope and saves it
放进信封里存起来，
because she's always worried about
因为她总是担心钱不够用。
having enough I go wow that's tough um
我会说：“哇，这太难了，
where do you think she got that from and
你觉得她这种性格是从哪儿来的？”
then Mom starts crying always I can have
然后妈妈就开始哭。我有时会遇到
a very um difficult financial situation
非常困难的经济状况，
uh two parents they'll be in $150,000 of
父母双方都会…… 面对15万美元的
credit card debt they're stoic about it
信用卡债务，他们表现得很冷静，选择视而不见。
they ignore it we talk about it they
我们谈论这件事，他们也会
engage but the minute I bring up the
参与，但只要我一提起，
kids tears and the reason for that is
孩子们就会哭。原因在于，一个人
that you can take on a lot of Burden
可以承受很多负担，
yourself but when you realize that your
但当你意识到自己的
behavior is being passed on to your kids
行为正在传递给孩子时，
that is really difficult and that's why
这真的很难接受。这就是为什么
couples can get on the same page and
夫妻需要达成共识，
build a healthy relationship for their
为孩子建立健康的亲子关系。
kids as well so what would you say then
那么，你会对孩子说什么呢？孩子
to your kid says Dad I want to be rich
说：“爸爸，我想变得富有。”
you said amazing great love it y tell me
你会说：“太棒了，我喜欢！告诉我
what it means and they say what are the
这意味着什么？” 孩子又会问：“
principles for wealth creation dad in
爸爸，创造财富的原则是什么？如何才能
keeping that money so that I can be
保住钱，实现
financially free it would be number one
财务自由？” 你会说：第一，
you have to find something you love to
你必须找到自己热爱的事情，努力
do work hard you have to love to work
工作，你必须热爱工作，
okay in your own way whatever it is
用你自己的方式去做，无论是什么。
two automatically invest every single
第二，每个月都要进行自动投资，这
month right that's great and number
很棒。
three you have to enjoy money enjoy it
第三，你必须享受金钱，享受它，不仅仅是赚钱，
but also spending it and if they said
不仅仅是管理，还要享受花钱。如果孩子问：“
Dad should I get credit cards I said
爸爸，我应该办信用卡吗？” 我会说：“
sure of course when the time is right
当然可以，时机成熟的时候
you should get a credit card you should
你可以办信用卡，但一定要按时
always pay it off every month but you
还款。” 每个月都放假，但你
should get a credit card and when you
应该办一张信用卡，等你
start to spend enough probably get a
消费达到一定金额后，可以考虑办一张
rewards card you can get some free trips
奖励卡，这样就能获得一些免费旅行
or cash back out of it notice that I'm
或现金返还。注意，我并
not being restrictive if they say I want
没有限制他们。如果他们说想
to buy coffee every day I would say
每天买咖啡，我会说
fantastic let's talk about how you can
太好了，我们来谈谈怎么才能
earn enough so you never have to worry
赚到足够的钱，这样你就不用再
about coffee if they even said to me I
为咖啡发愁了。如果他们甚至跟我说
want to buy a Lamborghini I'm not a
想买一辆兰博基尼，我虽然不是
Lamborghini guy I couldn't care less I
兰博基尼的拥趸，也根本不在乎，但我
would say amazing how do you think you
会说太棒了，你觉得你
could do that and what if they said oh
能做到吗？如果他们说，哦，
um you know I want to be a school
你知道，我想当一名
teacher I would say okay you know have
教师，我会说，好的，你有没有
you talked to any school teachers and
和任何一位教师聊过，
asked them how much they make then
问问他们挣多少钱？然后
calculate how long it would take you to
算算你需要多久才能
buy a Lamborghini kids are smart they
买得起一辆兰博基尼？孩子们很聪明，他们
can do these things we just have to
能做到这些，我们只需要
challenge them they say Dad I've only
挑战他们。他们会说，爸爸，我
got my pocket money so how am I going to
只有零花钱，我怎么才能
become an investor I don't have enough M
成为投资者？我没有足够的
money yet how much do you need to invest
钱，你需要投资多少钱？
I assume you need like, of pounds what
我猜你需要大约几英镑。
if I told you you only need to start
如果我告诉你，你只需要从几英镑开始呢？
with $100 I don't have $100 I have S
100美元？我没有100美元，我只有S
pound pocket money have you asked anyone
英镑的零花钱。你问过其他人
else how you could make an extra
怎么才能多赚
$93 no okay what could you do to ask
93美元吗？没有。好吧，那你可以让
them to make $93 what could you do clean
他们做什么来赚93美元呢？你可以做什么？比如擦
the cars in the street keep going I
街上的车？到处跑？我到处送
paper around and on and on and on so
报纸等等等等。所以，
here I'm not giving them the answer I'm
我不是在给他们答案，我是在
challenging them to learn how to think
挑战他们，让他们学会独立思考，
for themselves and to make $93 for a kid
并努力赚到93美元。对一个孩子来说，
you could do it it won't happen in one
你能做到，虽然不可能
day but you could do it very very
一天就做到，但你可以很快做到。
quickly how much money do you think you
你觉得你
need to start investing you should start
需要多少钱才能开始投资？你应该
investing as soon as you can you could
尽早开始投资，你可以从
start investing with 50 bucks a month my
每月50美元开始投资。我14岁的时候，我
my dad helped me open up a custodial
爸爸帮我开了一个托管
account when I was 14 years old so I
账户，所以我从那时起就
started investing then and my dad
开始投资了。我爸爸是
immigrated from India so I was very
从印度移民过来的，所以我很
lucky that he pushed me um but if you're
幸运，他一直鼓励我投资。如果你是
a parent you should definitely be
家长，你绝对应该
getting your kids to invest early even
让你的孩子尽早开始投资，即使
50 bucks a month makes a huge difference
每月50美元也能产生巨大的影响。
so you invested at 14 yeah and I've been
所以你14岁就开始投资了？是的，我
investing ever since and how did that do
从那时起就一直在投资。 那对
for you fantastic you know why because I
你来说效果很好，你知道为什么吗？因为我
sold I never sold almost anything it
卖掉了，我几乎没卖过任何东西，
single month no magic no random like
每个月的每一笔投资都保持不变，没有什么神奇的
amazing stock picks except for a couple
成分股，也没有什么随机的、令人惊艳的选股，除了少数几个
lucky ones it's just basically almost
幸运的股票之外，基本上都是
all index funds just every single month
指数基金，每个月都是如此。那加密
crypto I mean if you want to have it as
货币呢？我的意思是，如果你想把它作为
one to 5% of your portfolio as
你投资组合的1%到5%用于投机，那当然
speculation fantastic the problem is
很好。问题是，
that crypto investors I talk to don't
我接触过的加密货币投资者不
believe in diversification they will
相信多元化，他们
often have all their money in it and
通常会把所有的钱都投进去，而且
they don't really they don't follow
他们并不真正遵循
classic principles of investing and the
经典的投资原则。最
worst part is it's hard to argue when
糟糕的是，当加密货币表现
it's done so well so people go like what
如此出色时，很难反驳，所以人们会说，
the do you know 7% that sucks
你他妈的才知道7%？太糟糕了，
Grandpa and I go all right fine it has
老爷爷。我会说，好吧，它的
performed incredibly well at least in
表现确实非常出色，至少在
certain parts of crypto but you do not
某些加密货币领域是这样，但你不
want to have the majority of your assets
应该把大部分资产都放在
in one thing and it's the problem with
单一资产上。这也是
crypto as well is you only hear when
加密货币的问题所在，你只能在
it's doing well exactly so whenever the
它表现好的时候听到消息。没错，每当
the bare Market comes in everybody goes
裸市来临时，每个人都变得
quite quiet they get very quiet where'd
非常安静，非常安静。
you go guys sometimes I follow with them
你们都去哪儿了？有时我
on Twitter half the time their account
在推特上关注他们，但有一半时间他们的账号都被
deleted that's called survivorship bias
删除了。 那叫幸存者偏差，
you only hear about things when they're
你只会在事情好的时候听到消息，一旦出了问题，
good the minute it's bad account deleted
账号就被删除，
never heard from them again what about
再也联系不上了。
gambling you must see some gambling in
赌博呢？你肯定在
relationships I'm not sure how legal
恋爱关系中见过赌博吧？我不确定
gambling is in every state over here in
在美国每个州赌博的合法性如何，
the USA but in the UK gambling is legal
但在英国赌博是合法的，
so yeah it's often an issue in
所以赌博经常会成为恋爱关系中的一个问题，一个
relationships a quiet issue yeah it is a
隐秘的问题。是的，这是一个
quiet issue I think um I don't hear
隐秘的问题，我想，嗯，我不太
about it too often I suspect that um
常听到有人谈论它。我怀疑
gamblers simply don't want to talk about
赌徒只是不想谈论
it yeah which is actually the worst of
它，是的，这其实是最糟糕的。
all maybe I need to find a way to reach
也许我需要找到一种方法去接触
some gamblers I mean we do hear some
一些赌徒。我的意思是，我们确实听到一些非常
really tragic stuff we hear about um
悲惨的事情，比如
folks who have lost money on bad
有人在
Investments late in life we hear about
晚年因为糟糕的投资而赔钱，听到
parents whose kids are bleeding them dry
父母被子女榨干的故事，
but we also hear about some really
但我们也听到一些非常
positive things you know couples who who
积极的事情，比如一些夫妻
have quietly accumulated money over time
默默地积累了财富，
and they just don't realize we made it
他们只是没有意识到自己已经成功了。
and sometimes I get to do the very
有时我会很
pleasant thing of saying like hey you
愉快地对他们说：“嘿，你们
two clearly love each other you've done
俩显然彼此相爱，你们
this together you made it have have you
一起做到了，你们成功了！”你
ever seen marriages fall apart because
见过婚姻因为赌博而破裂吗？ 在
of these issues we've had couples break
这些问题上，我们遇到过一些情侣在
up directly after our podcast marriages
播客节目播出后直接分手的情况。
of course I get emails all the time the
当然，我经常收到这样的邮件，说
reason that we broke up was money but
他们分手的原因是钱。但
you know what's interesting research
你知道吗，有趣的研究
shows which I cite in the book that um
表明（我在书中也引用过），
when couples fight they don't fight
当情侣吵架时，他们
about money you know what they fight
吵的并不是钱，而是
kids chores and
孩子、家务和
communication money is rarely talked
沟通。钱很少被提及，
about it's only talked about when
只有在吵架的时候才会被提及，
there's a fight but it's the least of
但它却是
what people are typically arguing about
人们争吵的最小原因。
kids chores communication that's what
孩子、家务和沟通才是人们
gets fought about unromantic though
争吵的焦点。虽然这很不浪漫，但人们似乎对
a stigma don't talk about money and yeah
谈论金钱有一种偏见，这很荒谬。
which is crazy I I encourage couples to
我鼓励情侣
have a monthly money meeting I even give
每月开一次“财务会议”，我甚至会给
them an exact agenda here's the Google
他们一份详细的议程。这是谷歌
Doc work it out adapt it for your own
文档，你可以根据自己的
needs start off with a compliment you
需要进行调整。以赞美开始，比如：“
know I really appreciated that you
我真的很感谢你为
planned that trip for us to the
我们安排了去
grandparents like the you did such a
爷爷奶奶家的旅行，你安排的
great job with flights start off like
机票太棒了！”就这样开始。
that people look at me like I'm speaking
人们看着我，好像我在滔滔不绝地讲述，紧紧抓住不放。
cling on to them an agenda for my wife
给妻子准备一份议程
or my husband I go what they go that's
？ 我丈夫，我去哪儿都行，这很
weird I go I think it's weird for you to
奇怪。我觉得很奇怪，你们
go 40 years fighting about money never
40年来一直在为钱争吵，从来不
talking about it never creating a
谈论钱，从来不制定
vision instead of using an agenda it's
计划，而是各怀心思。这
so interesting because you know much of
很有意思，因为你知道，
the issues in my household growing up
我成长过程中家里的很多问题都与
were money related so between my my
钱有关，所以我父母之间……
that my mother had any idea how much
我母亲根本不可能知道
money my dad had or how much money the
我有多少钱 爸爸以前有多少钱，或者说
household had wow and I really as you
家里有多少钱，哇！你刚才
were saying it now I thought God if they
说的时候，我真想，天哪，如果他们
just sat down once and had that
当初能坐下来好好
conversation like how much money do we
谈谈，比如“我们家
actually have here God our childhood
到底有多少钱”，我们的童年该有多不
would have been so drastically different
一样啊！
let's pause for a minute to talk about
我们先停一下，聊聊
today's sponsor which is whoop I often
今天的赞助商——Whoop。我经常
think how lucky we are to live in a time
想，我们生活在一个
where we can so easily access
可以如此轻松获取
information on how our body is
身体状况信息的时代，真是太幸运了。
performing but it also makes me wonder
但这也让我不禁思考，究竟有
how many of us are really utilizing this
多少人真正利用了这项
technology a couple of years ago I
技术。几年前，我
started wearing whoop a device that
开始佩戴Whoop，这是一款可以
monitors how activities and behaviors
监测活动和行为如何
affect my sleep my training my recovery
影响我的睡眠、训练、恢复
and my stress I'm currently Midway
和压力水平的设备。我目前正在
through whoop sober October Challenge
参加Whoop的“十月戒酒挑战”，
and this month if I compare it to a time
这个月，如果我和
when I used to drink my stress levels
以前喝酒的时候相比，我的压力水平
are significantly lower if you're like
明显降低了。如果你也像
me and you're aiming to be the best
我一样，渴望成为更好的
version of yourself then you have to go
自己，那就赶紧去
and check out whoop head to join.
了解一下Whoop吧！点击这里加入。
woop.com CEO to start your free trial
woop.com CEO，今天就开始你的免费试用吧！
today and if you're already a whoop
如果你已经是woop
member taking part in this challenge do
会员并参与了这项挑战，请帮
me a favor send me a DM a message and
我个忙，给我发个私信，
let me know how you're getting on do you
告诉我你的进展如何。你
know you said you are at a point where
知道你说过
you now think you have enough yeah but
你现在觉得已经足够了，是的，但
you're still striving for more and still
你仍然在努力追求更多，仍然在
investing and still earning and still
投资，仍然在赚钱，仍然
waking up every day and driving then
每天醒来开车。这就是
why I like it I love what I do I love
我喜欢它的原因。我热爱我的
working I um the more that I make the
工作，我热爱我的事业。嗯，我赚的越多，就越能
more that it is a sign I'm creating
证明我在创造
value that's it but I
价值，就是这样。但我会
systematically earn more like I have my
系统地赚更多，我有自己的
rules so for example unexpected income
规则。例如，对于意外收入，我
that comes in 70 to 90% of that will be
会将其中70%到90%用于
invested right meaning like I'll take
投资，对吧？也就是说，我会拿出
10% and have a good time but I'm
10%来享受生活，但我
primarily investing unexpected income
主要还是把意外收入用于投资。
question then if you got a$ 100 million
那么，如果你意外获得1亿美元，
windfall yeah how would your life
你的生活会如何
change it's hard to say I have a very
改变？很难说，我的
good life i100 million comes in what you
生活已经很好了。如果突然有1亿美元，你
going to do with
会怎么用？
it I
我的
mean it's going to change almost nothing
意思是，它几乎不会改变什么。
I would I would it would accelerate some
我会……我会…… 加快
of my plans for
我的一些
charity um for a house because I would
慈善计划，比如买房。因为我会先把
have the house drawn up even though I
房子设计好，虽然我
don't even want to buy a house anytime
近期并不打算买房，但
soon I would probably have the house
我可能会先把设计图画好，
drawn up and then I would say call me
然后告诉他们房子准备好了可以
when it's ready to move in and don't
入住的时候再联系我，在此之前不要
call me before then I I want nothing to
联系我。我不想
do with building it I don't want to see
参与建造，我不想看到
a piece of wood go over there why would
任何木头被搬到那里。
you buy a house purely because what else
你为什么要买房？除了买房，
are you going to do with the money of
你还能用这笔钱做什么？当然，
giveaway you got to spend the money
捐赠是必须的，你总得想办法花掉这笔钱，
somehow but
但
a why house what else you going to do
买房除了买房还能做什么？
with it just save it I already saved it
存起来？我已经存了，
I already invested it see what happens
我已经投资了。你看，
is when you start to as you know you
当你开始……你知道的，当你
start to hit your numbers and exceed
开始达到你的目标，甚至超出
them bigger than you ever thought
你想象的程度时，
possible you start to realize that so
你就会意识到，
much of our life is spent playing
我们生命中的大部分时间都花在了
defense with money that's the
与金钱的博弈上。这就是
relationship that most of us have with
我们大多数人与
money will we have enough at the grocery
金钱的关系：我们够不够钱去超市买东西？够不够钱
store will we have enough to fix the
修
window will we have enough to get a car
窗户？够不够钱买车？
and most people live that way but if you
大多数人都是这样生活的。但如果你
start to save automatically and you
开始养成自动储蓄的习惯，
start to invest and you really make it a
开始投资，并真正把这作为你的
focus to earn and understand how money
关注点…… 当你赚够钱，了解金钱的
works at a certain point you go oh my
运作方式后，你会突然意识到，
gosh objectively speaking looking at our
天哪，客观地看我们的
numbers we don't ever have to worry
财务状况，我们再也不用担心
about the price of a chicken bowl again
一碗鸡肉饭的价格了。那么，这
it all give it away I guess this is
一切的意义何在？难道要把钱捐出去吗？我
where I think um this is the real
想，这才是真正的
Challenge and you know a lot of retirees
挑战。很多退休人士
accumulated money and but they never
积累了不少钱，但他们从未
really thought about the point of it all
真正思考过这一切的意义。我
sometimes people um surprise me by how
有时会惊讶于人们在
uncreative they are with money I'll give
金钱方面的创造力。举个
you an example I ask people what is your
例子，我会问别人你的“
money dial what do you love to spend
金钱偏好”是什么，你最喜欢把
money on and um people they usually have
钱花在什么地方。人们通常都能给出
a pretty good answer the most common
不错的答案。最
answer is um food the next common answer
常见的答案是美食，其次是
is uh travel then health and wellness
旅行，然后是健康和养生，还有
and there's a bunch of other money dials
很多其他的“金钱偏好”。
so one guy once told me um I like
有个人曾经告诉我，他喜欢
coffee that that's his money dial coffee
咖啡，这就是他的“金钱偏好”——咖啡。我问他
I go what do you mean he goes I order
什么意思？他说，我会从不同的渠道订购
different beans from whatever I go can I
不同的咖啡豆。说实话，
by your answer cuz he he was doing very
你的答案让我感到无聊。 他当时表现得很好。
well I like okay you buy a $20 bag of
我心想，好吧，你花20美元买了一袋
coffee beans all right you have way more
咖啡豆，好吧，你
money and he's just like he was a little
钱多得很。他好像觉得
insulted that I said it but I was trying
我这么说有点冒犯他，但我当时只是在
to shake him because I was bored some
逗他，因为我闲着没事干。一个有那么多
person with that much money should not
钱的人不应该
be telling me that the thing they love
告诉我，他们唯一喜欢
to spend money on only is coffee so I go
花钱的地方就是咖啡。所以我就
listen you like making your own coffee
问他，你喜欢自己做咖啡吗？
he goes yeah I have my Aro press and
他说，是啊，我有压滤壶，还有这个那个。
this and that I go what if if you
我说，如果你
considered hiring the Barista from your
考虑请你家附近咖啡馆的咖啡师来
local place to come to your house and
你家，
show you how to fine-tune that coffee
教你如何更好地制作咖啡呢？
what if you really learn how to spend
如果你真的学会如何
money on that experience and deepen the
花钱体验咖啡，加深这种
experience it's not about buying 10 more
体验呢？这不是买十包
coffee bags it's about going deeper a
咖啡豆的问题，而是要更深入地了解咖啡。
year later or two years later we talked
一年或两年后，我们聊起这件事，他说
he had done that and he got really into
他真的这么做了，而且他
coffee he was now traveling to go to
现在非常痴迷咖啡。他开始去
different locations Colombia Rwanda all
不同的地方旅行，比如哥伦比亚、卢旺达等等，在那里
these places where he had started to
他开始
appreciate the coffee so sometimes we
欣赏当地的咖啡。所以有时候我们
need to get more creative you don't have
需要更有创意。你不必
to spend thousands of dollars but if you
花几千美元，但如果你
and your partner love this thing think
和你的伴侣都喜欢咖啡，那就想想
about how you can spend money to
你们可以如何花钱来享受咖啡。
appreciate it even more and your
更加珍惜它，你的
strategy is to then stop spending money
策略就是停止在那些
on the things that you don't appreciate
你不珍惜的东西上花钱。
yeah so this why your Rich Life vision
所以，这就是你的“富足生活愿景”的意义
comes in what do we care about what do
所在：我们关心什么？
we want to spend extravagantly on and
我们想在哪些方面挥霍？
then what do we want to cut cost
我们又想在哪些方面毫不留情地削减开支？
mercilessly on we always start with what
我们总是从我们想在哪些方面
do we want to spend more on so when I
多花钱开始。当我引导人们思考时，
people I have a variety of exercises I
我会做各种各样的练习，比如“
walk them through like what's your
你
perfect week I'll tell you that uh I've
理想的一周是什么样的？”。我告诉你，我和
done this with many many people not one
很多人一起做过这个练习，没有一个
person has ever said my perfect week
人说过“我理想的一周
involves doing
包括
laundry cool could we pay that out and
洗衣服”。太好了！我们可以把这部分支出提前实现吗？
if you can't afford to do that today
如果你现在负担不起，
that's okay put it on your vision and
没关系，把它写进你的愿景里，
say when we get to this number we're
告诉自己“当我们达到这个数字时，我们就再也
never going to do laundry again
不用洗衣服了”。
fantastic but it also gives you
太棒了！而且，这还能给你
something to look forward to you know
一些期待。你知道，人们常说，
it's thrown around that once household
一旦家庭
income equals x number then people are
收入达到某个数字，人们就会感到
happy or at least that there diminishing
幸福，或者至少
returns is it yeah that $75,000
收益递减。这纯属胡扯！没错，就是那个75000美元的
number first of all that was already
数字。首先，那已经是
like 10 years ago so we have to factor
10年前的数字了，所以我们必须
in inflation but second more recent
考虑通货膨胀。其次，最近的
research has show uh shown that actually
研究表明…… 研究表明，
happiness continues increasing there's
幸福感实际上会持续增长，
also self-satisfaction so there's a
自我满足感也是如此。所以，幸福感受
variety of different variables basically
多种因素影响。总之，
don't believe that $75,000 number that's
不要相信那些流传甚广的7.5万美元的说法，那根本毫无
tossed around it doesn't make any sense
意义。
what's more important is you create a
更重要的是，你们要共同创造一个
vision together and you go what would
愿景，然后思考：怎样才能
make this week this year this next 10
让这周、今年、未来
years amazing for us let's just put it
十年都过得精彩？让我们把
all out there it doesn't even matter if
所有想法都提出来，即使
we know how we can afford it or not then
我们不知道自己是否负担得起也没关系。然后，
let's talk about it do we know our
让我们讨论一下：我们是否了解自己的
numbers do we have enough can we pay for
财务状况？我们是否有足够的钱支付
our kids college or not can we buy an
孩子的大学学费？我们是否能买个
extra iPhone charger so we don't have to
备用的iPhone充电器，这样就不用
run to the bedroom every day and you
每天都跑到卧室去充电了？然后，你们
start to create and design your rich
开始共同创造和设计你们的富足
life together that's the way you do
生活。这就是幸福的真谛。这是一个
it very interesting topic and it's
非常有趣的话题，
particularly pertinent to me because you
对我来说尤其重要，因为正如我之前
know as I said I spoke to a divorce ly
提到的，我前几周和一位离婚律师聊过，
the other week and he told me that it's
他告诉我，
the one of the top two reasons couples
夫妻
get divorced is because of money
离婚的两大主要原因之一就是金钱
problems and I really didn't know what
问题。我当时真的不明白
he meant I thought maybe it's one of the
他的意思，我以为…… 可能是其中一方
partners loses all of their money and it
输光了所有积蓄，
causes arguments or maybe it's just that
引发争吵；也可能是因为双方对
money and it's kind of like the elephant
金钱问题讳莫如深，积怨已久，就像房间里的大象一样，始终无人
addressed and this is exactly what you
提及。而这正是你
try and do in this book and you do it so
在这本书里试图探讨的，而且你做得非常
masterfully your first book is sold you
出色。你的第一本书就卖出了
know seven figures worth of copies and I
七位数的销量，我完全
understand why and I have a sneaking
理解为什么。我隐隐觉得
suspicion that this book is going to be
这本书也会
equally successful because it is the
同样成功，因为金钱问题
elephant in the room in most
在大多数
relationships the fact that you know
关系中都是一个难以启齿的话题。
when I saw that you'd written a book
当我看到你写了一本
about money for couples it immediately
关于夫妻理财的书时，
made me realize I go Chris we've never
我立刻意识到，克里斯，我们从来没有
talked about that in our relationship
在关系中谈论过这个问题，
and why not and it's a whole complex
为什么呢？这其中有很多复杂的
Myriad of reasons and Trauma and uh
原因，包括创伤、
emotions and insecurities and shame but
情绪、不安全感和羞耻感。但就像
like all things in my relationship the
我关系中所有的事情一样，
more talking I did about it the better
我谈论得越多，情况就越好，这个
it became and the less of a an issue it
问题也就越不突出。
became and you know there's almost a
你知道，在人际关系中，金钱和人际关系之间似乎存在某种
correlation in relationships isn't there
关联，不是吗？
between the amount you talk about an
你谈到了一个
issue and how big the issue is um and
问题，以及这个问题有多严重，嗯，
that relates to all things whether it's
这涉及到方方面面，无论是
sex or if it's the in-laws or it's
性、姻亲关系、
friendships or whatever it might be so
友谊，还是其他任何事情。所以这本书出版的时机非常
it's a really well-timed book and I've
合适，我
really not discovered one quite like it
还没发现过类似的书，
so I highly recommend everybody goes and
所以我强烈推荐大家去看看。这本书
checks it out it's out in December um
12月出版，
the link is below so if you're listening
链接在下面。如果你现在正在听
to this now you should be able to
这个节目，你应该可以
pre-order this book right now and
预购这本书了。
hopefully this can form the Foundation
希望这本书能为你们的感情关系奠定基础，开启一段
of a conversation that you very much
你们非常需要进行的对话，这段对话或许能
that might just save your
挽救你们的
relationship such a pleasure we have a
感情。很高兴听到你来。我们
closing tradition on the podcast where
播客有个结尾的传统，上一位
the last guest leaves a question to the
嘉宾会在CEO的日记里给下一位嘉宾留下一个问题。
question that's been left for
留给
you is what can you do to improve
你的问题是：你能做些什么来改善
humanity and the life of
人类和人们的生活？我
people I think in my world the best
认为，在我的世界里，
thing I can do is
我能做的最好的事情就是
uh set an example of someone who
树立一个榜样，公开
publicly speaks about the things that
谈论那些对我来说
are important to them who wakes up every
重要的事情，每天醒来都充满热情地去
day and has a great time teaching loves
教书，热爱
what I do
我的工作，
and models having a loving relationship
并以身作则地与人们建立充满爱的关系。 是的，你以身作则，在
me yeah leading by example in every
各个方面都堪称楷模。非常
word thank you so much such a pleasure
感谢你，和你聊天真是太愉快了，
to speak to you and you've open my eyes
你让我大开眼界。
to so many things and every time I have
每次和别人
these conversations I hope that uh I
交流，我都希望能够获得
walk away with some kind of actionable
一些切实可行的
insight into something that matters in
见解，这些见解对
my life and that's certainly the case in
我的生活至关重要。
this conversation so thank thank you so
这次的谈话也确实如此。非常感谢你今天再次光临，谢谢你。
[Music]
[音乐]
you every single time you eat you have
每一次进食都是
an opportunity to improve your health
改善健康的机会，
and that's why I love Zoe because Zoe
这就是我喜欢Zoe的原因，因为Zoe
helps me to make the smartest food
帮助我做出最适合
choices for me and my body and as you
我身体的明智食物选择。你们
guys will know by now Zoe is a sponsor
现在应该都知道，Zoe是
of this podcast and I'm an investor in
这个播客的赞助商，而我也是这家
the company and if you haven't tried Zoe
公司的投资人。如果你还没试过Zoe，
I highly recommend you do because Zoe
我强烈推荐你试试，因为Zoe
combines My Health Data with Zoe's World
结合了我的健康数据和Zoe世界
Class science and using those two things
一流的科学技术，并利用这两方面，在
single time I make a food choice and eat
每次我做出食物选择和进食时，Zoe都能指导我走向更健康的未来。这
which means that I have more energy
意味着我精力更充沛、
better sleep better mood and I'm less
睡眠更好、心情更愉悦，而且也不那么容易感到
hungry and the most important thing is
饥饿。最重要的是，
Zoe actually works it's backed by their
Zoe真的有效，他们
recent clinical trial something called
最近的临床试验也证实了这一点。 我使用了一种叫做
the method study which is the gold
方法研究的方法，这是
standard of scientific research I
科学研究的黄金标准。我
started Zoe just over a year ago now and
一年多前开始使用 Zoe，
I've been able to track my progress week
每周都能追踪自己的进步，
after week so I can learn how to be even
这样我就可以学习如何
smarter the following week and if you
在下一周变得更聪明。如果你
haven't joined Zoe yet I'm giving you
还没有加入 Zoe，
10% off when you join Zoe now just use
现在加入 Zoe 可以享受 10% 的折扣，
the code ce10 at checkout
结账时只需使用代码 ce10 即可。
[Music]
[音乐]
oh
哦